<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The town adventurer. A discourse of masquerades, playes, &amp;c. By Don Francisco de Quevedo, Junior.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1976B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833541</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2067:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The town adventurer. A discourse of masquerades, playes, &amp;c. By Don Francisco de Quevedo, Junior.</title>
                  <author>Quevedo, Francisco de, 1580-1645. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 170 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Baile, and are to be sold by H. Eversden, at the Crown in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange, and at the ... the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>167[5]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata on the verso of the title page.</note>
                  <note>Formerly Wing (2nd ed.) Q194.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page torn affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TOWN ADVENTURER. A DISCOURSE OF MASQUERADES, PLAYES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Don Franciſco de Quevedo,</hi> Junior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Baile,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>H. Everſden,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Strand.</hi> 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:38018:2"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 21. read ill, p. 7. l. 17. add and. p. 9. l. 4. add what, p. 26. l. 23. r. aire, p. 27. l. 9. r. enjoying. p. 34. l. 11. r. ſo, l. 17. r. Town, p. 33. l. 26. r. a few, p. 38. l. ult, add what, p. 47. l. 11. add he, p. 49. l. 15. r. avowing, p. 51. l. 22. 1. hid, p. 58. l. 10. add him, p. 66. l. 20. <hi>r.</hi> ſtrangely, p. 69. l. 17. r. when, l. 19. r. where, p. 70. l. 26. r. incomparably, p. 72. l. ult. r. from, p. 74. l. 20. r. in, p. 80. l. 7. r. ſort. p. 87. l. 2. r. Maid, p. 112. l. 14. r. then is, p. 117. l. 7. r. Rack.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:38018:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THe Loves of <hi>Altophel</hi> at Home.</item>
               <item>2. The Occaſion of his coming to Town.</item>
               <item>3. The Humour of <hi>Rhoderick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Rencounters in his Travel.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Altophels</hi> Faſhion and Addreſſes.</item>
               <item>6. The Miſadventures of <hi>Rhoderick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. A Trick put upon <hi>Altophel</hi> by two Ladies.</item>
               <item>8. Another of his Miſadventures, in which he Loſes his Cloathes.</item>
               <item>9. <hi>Altophel</hi> is ſet upon by a Lady at a Ball, who Accuſes him of unlrand ſome Actions.</item>
               <item>10. A Trick put upon his two Friends by a Love-Letter.</item>
               <item>11. <hi>Altophel</hi> falls Paſſionately in Love with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Lady.</item>
               <item>12. He is carried to a Bawdy Houſe by <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and others, where he receives an Affront.</item>
               <item>13. The ſame Company are Encountred by the Watch, by whom they are Diſarmed, and after Reſcued by ſome unknown Gentlemen.</item>
               <item>14. <hi>Altophel,</hi> whilſt he purſues his Love to the fair unknown, is taken Notice of by <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> who ſtudies to make a Divertiſment of it.</item>
               <item>15. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> by a counterfeit Letter, makes him an Aſſignation in the Name of the unknown La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, where he meets with great Perplexities.</item>
               <item>16. An Account of <hi>Altophels</hi> Extravagant Jealouſie, and the Deſcription of a Town Lady. His Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt a Gentleman at a Ball, concerning words <hi>Al-a-Mode.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17. <hi>Altophel</hi> is Engaged in a Duel upon the account of his Miſtreſs, by whom they are parted.</item>
               <item>18. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> is Arreſted for the Debt of one of his Women, and <hi>Altophel</hi> becomes his Bail.</item>
               <item>19. The Concluſion of <hi>Altophels</hi> Amours with his unknown Miſtreſs: With an account of the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Generoſity of that Lady.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:38018:3"/>
               <item>20. <hi>Altophel</hi> applies himſelf to the Society of the Wits.</item>
               <item>21. <hi>Altophels</hi> Diſpute with <hi>Rhoderick</hi> concerning Wit, Poetry, and the Pellum Poeticum.</item>
               <item>22. <hi>Altophels</hi> becoming Acquainted with two very great Wits, his Miſadventures with their, and two Ladies at a Tavern.</item>
               <item>23. His Diſpute with one of thoſe Gentlemen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Poetry.</item>
               <item>24. A great Extravagance acted by <hi>Altophel, Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> the two Wits, and two Ladies.</item>
               <item>25. The Miſadventure of a great Lawyer.</item>
               <item>26. <hi>Altophels</hi> Reſolution to return Home with the Reaſons that obliged him to it.</item>
               <item>27. His Reception from his Parents, and from <hi>Aſtraea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>28. The great Generoſity and Honour of <hi>Aſtraea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>29. <hi>Altophels</hi> renewed Addreſſes to her.</item>
               <item>30. The Mutual Reſolutions of <hi>Altophel,</hi> and <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> alwayes to Live unmarried.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38018:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECTION. I.</hi> Series of Love.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALtophel,</hi> who was Born to a conſiderable Fortune in <hi>Cleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having Run through all the Parts of a Remote and Plain Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, he at laſt (as the Faſhion of ſuch young Gentlemen is) happen'd to fall in Love; the Time of his Age, with the Leiſure and Receſs of his Affairs, did not more forcibly Engage him in that Paſſion, than the innocent Charms of <hi>Aſtraea:</hi> She had all that Nature could do to make her a Sweet and Amiable Creature, without being Obliged to Art and uſeleſs Imbelliſhments. In <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraea</hi> was a perfect Symmetry and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; in her Face was an amiable mixture of Roſes and Lillies, to which belong'd an admirable Shape, and a graceful Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; her Mind was the moſt Innocent and free from Artifice on the one hand, &amp;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38018:4"/>Affectation on the other; She under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood her ſelf well enough in all things that belong'd to the Reputation and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her Sex, and took ſuch a true Account of her own good Qualities, as was Neceſſary to keep her from being Rude to Innocent Addreſſes, or enſnared in a Flattering Courtſhip; all theſe were enough at the ſame time to Enamour <hi>Altophel,</hi> and yet to keep him in that Decorum which was Due to her Birth and Quality; they were both under the Government of Parents, Tender enough, and yet Severe at the ſame time, but Love, that is the moſt ready at Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving its own Affairs, ſoon Taught our Lovers to Frame all their Interviews without their Knowledge; the Youth found in <hi>Aſtraea</hi> no greater averſion for his Flame, than the neceſſary Punctilioes of her Sex obliged her to in the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of a Paſſion: In ſhort (for I have but little to ſay in this part of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophels</hi> Life) They Contracted a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friendſhip; agreeable Qualities, and different Sexes, made them Love intirely. They every moment wiſht to be with each other; and when their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs kept them aſſunder, they were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38018:4"/>perpetually contriving of ſudden Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views <hi>Altophel</hi> was neither Unlovely nor Unbred, <hi>Aſtraea</hi> was Charming and Accompliſht; and it was impoſſible, when they had once begun to Love, but that they ſhould do it with the greateſt ardor. A perpetual Converſation and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, even with things of little Value, yet by a conſtant Tract they make on the Mind, leave the impreſſions of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Dearneſs, and eſpecially where there are excellent Qualities in that with whom we Converſe and Mingle inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, there muſt needs be a very great Concernment. <hi>I</hi> am willing to believe that in thoſe Moments, <hi>Altophel</hi> could freely have Died for <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> nor would ſhe haue been Indebted to him for that Generous proof of his Paſſion; had any offer'd him the moſt Beautiful Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in exchange for <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> he would have deſpiſed the Magnificence nor could any have removed <hi>Altophel</hi> out of her Breſt, though the Competitor had been a Monarch. They avow'd the ſame things to each other under The Mirtles and the Shades, whether they fled to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their innocent Paſſions: Nay, when they parted, they went away Diſſatisfied
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38018:5"/>from thoſe Interviews, if they had made to each other Proteſtations leſs full and ardent, than the moſt Inflamed affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons could Inſpire them with: They en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed about a Year this Agreeable life, and without doubt it was the moſt pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Altophel</hi> or <hi>Aſtraea</hi> will ever know. Thoſe accidents which Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted it, was the Deſign of <hi>Aſtraeas</hi> Friends to beſtow her in Marriage upon another Perſon. <hi>Altophel</hi> had a Fortune great enough to have pretended publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her, but we are ever unwilling to Expoſe that Paſſion, whoſe Intereſts we have been wont to Manage in private. <hi>Aſtraeas</hi> Friends propoſed to her that Perſon whom they intended for her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, on whom ſhe looked with a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Averſion, as having Choſen before, and as having no Room left in her Soul, that was not poſſeſs'd by <hi>Altophel;</hi> but though ſhe entertained all things that belong'd to this new Servant, with the greateſt Diſpleaſure, and as being by his Addreſſes deprived of thoſe Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſhe uſed to have of meeting <hi>Altophel,</hi> yet it was impoſſible for her to Remove thoſe Inconveniencies, and though ſhe Repreſented them to <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38018:5"/>yet he coming often to their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places, and ſhe being forced fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to fail him, he began without any reaſon to be Jealous of her; the occaſion of theſe Suſpitions, ariſing from Cauſes ſo Nice and Critical, are little ſubject to the Cenſure of indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Perſons; for Jealouſie that appears ſo Capricious to all the World that are in humour, does yet ſeem to have very good grounds to an Intereſſed Perſon: This is certain, that a Thouſand Cares are perpetually watching the beloved Treaſure of the Mind, there is no Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though it be the moſt aſſured of its Object, and the beſt ſatisfied with its own Pretences, but will Create an infinite Number of Perplexities to it ſelf, which yet can be aſcribed to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe but the overflowings of Love; yet Jealouſie has this which is all in it, that it may wrongfully accuſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Innocence and Juſtice, and become extreamly troubleſome to thoſe in whoſe Power it is not to Cure by the moſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect Behaviour. That Kindneſs muſt be extreamly Valued, for whoſe ſake we can ſet our ſelves to humour all the Capriciouſneſs of an unreaſonable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38018:6"/>fear; and it proves almoſt a Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the Affection which we have for any one, to find it Diſtruſted; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt there is a neceſſity of a great deal of Vertue, and a great deal of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Government of an excellent Paſſion; and Love, to which is aſcribed the Titles of Blind, Raſh and Childiſh, ought to have both the beſt Eye-ſight, and the beſt Judgment. How <hi>Altophel</hi> conceived, and how he conducted his Jealouſie we never were ſo curious as to Learn, and all the Knowledge that we have received of it, is only by the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</p>
            <p>Though the Parents of <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> not knowing her Affection, took no Care to Diſcover it by her Actions; yet her Lover ſupplied that Defect, and took an Account of all the Moments that were properly hers; He failed not to render her the moſt conſtant Viſits, and in that which he deſigned to appear Gallant, he was extreamly Inſupportable and Tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to her; but ſhe could not Rid her ſelf of that Trouble, as Diſagreeable as it was to her, and ſhe was forced not only to Endure that, but to neglect a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which the preſent ill Humour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38018:6"/>of <hi>Altophel</hi> ſeemed to require from her; ſometimes (it is true) they met, but the Entertainment which Jealouſie in him, and the deepeſt Diſcontent in her made them afford to each other, is much better Omitted than Remembred; as we are willing to forget (our ſelves) all thoſe things we have done, when we were ill Natur'd and out of Humour, ſo it is a part of very great Civility to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the Recording of them. So far this Jealouſie had its Effects, that <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> believed himſelf forſaken by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraea,</hi> and the Diſtracted Youth could not but believe, but that he which had all her time had equal meaſures of her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was both Abandoned to her Love as well as her Converſation; it could not be expected but that ſuch Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſettled in the Mind of an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Youth, muſt produce Effects very Extravagant. He was too young to have any great Judgment to aſſiſt him againſt this Jealouſie, and though every mans Underſtanding will be willing to Dictate theſe two things to the Lover; firſt, That we ſhould truſt every one to the Conduct of their own Vertue, which will more effectually keep them from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38018:7"/>an ill Action, than all our Suſpitions and Fears can poſſibly doe; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That the moſt valued Perſon in the World by doing an unjuſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Action, puts an end in that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all that Affection we have for them, yet without doubt there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that can more readily approve of the Truth of theſe Preſcriptions, than put them in Execution in thoſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that require their aid. <hi>Altophel</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to eaſe himſelf of his Preſſures by Removing from Home, and there was then at his Fathers Houſe a young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that had ſpent moſt of his time at <hi>London,</hi> and that affected in all Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies where he came, to be Eſteemed a Man of the Town; he was upon quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Country, and <hi>Altophel</hi> addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf to his Parents, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he might Accompany him, to ſee ſome of thoſe things to which he was wholly a Stranger: He obtained their Conſent at the firſt Asking, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly prepared himſelf for the Journey. It is not neceſſary to Determine with what Injuſtice the Love-ſtruck youth leſt his <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> and a Paſſion in which he had took ſo many Engagements, only
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38018:7"/>to ſeek the moſt Extravagant eaſe in the World; ſuch was his Reſolution, and ſuch the Execution of it, it generally hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens in Actions of this Nature, that we call Civility and Good-breeding are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver permitted to have a ſhare in thoſe Actions we dedicate to our Reſentment, it is hard to aſſign the Reaſon why we ſhould Excuſe them: Certainly, the being in Love is no Plea for Rudeneſs or ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet it is manifeſt that <hi>Altophel</hi> acted contrary, both to his Civility and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; for he never Communicated any thing of his Reſolution to <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> not took his Leave of her. If ſuch things are a Revenge in Love, they can only ſatisfie the Perſon who deſigns them as ſuch, whilſt they are matters of Reproach to all others; Why we ſhould not have always the greateſt Reſpect for thoſe whom ye have ſerved with the moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Paſſion, is found a Difficulty only in the Breſt of a Lover; And ſuch an one was <hi>Altophel,</hi> he believed it would look Ridiculouſly to give <hi>Aſtraea</hi> any Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Going, as if it had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to procure her Intreaties for his ſtay, or whether he believed ſhe was not at Leiſure to think upon it; he would
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38018:8"/>not try her Temper in that particular; but the firſt News ſhe had of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, was after he had made a conſiderable Progreſs in it: The faithful <hi>Aſtraea</hi> was ſtruck to the heart with this extravagant Unkindneſs, and it was Difficult for her to Interpret it, whilſt ſhe knew the great Uprightneſs of her own Mind; ſhe had ever believed him ſatisfied with that Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in which ſhe her ſelf could find no Blemiſh, and ſhe had been free from the Suſpition of ſuch a thing in him, whilſt ſhe had ever meaſured his Paſſion by her own: She grieved, and ſhe Forgave <hi>Altophel</hi> in the ſame moment, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that whatever was the Rule of His Actions, the greateſt Juſtice ſhould be that of Hers. She was far from thinking that a neglected or a wrong'd Fidelity became any thing of a Reproach, ſince there is ever ſomething brave in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting of an Injured kindneſs againſt our Reſentments; if there is any thing that ought to be Reproach'd, it is the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and the Rudeneſs of thoſe that forſake, whilſt a juſt Perſeverance ever appears worthy of the greateſt Elogies. Here we muſt for ſome time leave <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraea</hi> to her Grief, and Injured kindneſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38018:8"/>enduring the Importunities of a Rival to that Love ſhe was reſolved to preſerve againſt all Aſſaults, and the Diſpleaſure of her Friends for not Complying with thoſe things that were contrary to it; ſhe will do all things worthy of her Self, and the greateſt Glorys of her Sex, and ſhe will Merit a fairer Commendation than the Extravagant <hi>Altophel</hi> will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, for thoſe things we are about to deſcribe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38018:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Character of the Town Gallant.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALtophels</hi> Friend, whom we will know by the Name of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> could not but take Notice of his ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, which yet he did not Interpret as any thing of Love, but the dulneſs of a Barren and private Education<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; Perſons of a pleaſant and Airy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, are apt to Diſcredit every<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thing that is not of the ſame <hi>Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and reproach it as an Ignorance of the Town-Breeding: We cannot ſay much in Commendation of <hi>Altophels</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Humour, without doubt; a Perſon under thoſe Circumſtances as he was in, is the worſt Company in the World. But <hi>Rhoderick</hi> reſolved to ſhew his Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in doing Wonders on a piece of <hi>Northern</hi> Dulneſs, as he Termed our Squire, he read him ſo many fine Lectures on the <hi>Janty</hi> things of the Town, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38018:9"/>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> reſolved to give himſelf ſo much Leiſure as to be Inſtructed in them, and which <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was ſo willing to give him the Knowledge of. Their manner of Travelling was in the Stage Coach, where they had the Company of two Ladies, with another Perſon: <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> told the Squire, that if he would do any thing Gallant, he muſt make Love to one of thoſe Beauties, and to Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him, he gave him the choice of his Miſtreſs, aſſuring him that he would keep him Company in Courting the other. I have all this while forgot to give you the Character of <hi>Rhoderick</hi> (and indeed it is ſomething difficult to do it) there are ſo many things which Perſons of that Humour pretend to, and ſo many Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings about, that it is hard to bring their Accompliſhments together into a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; he was a man very Hardy in all his actions, very Opinionative of himſelf, very Vindictive of his own Principles, and very Cenſorious; he was perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hunting after new Adventures, and yet all theſe things ſeemed to acknowledg the Aſcendant of ſome higher Rules and Meaſures of acting. But thoſe were ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38018:10"/>Confuſed and Extravagant, that it is impoſſible to Range them into any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</p>
            <p>He had a Smatch of a Thouſand Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and as many different Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, at one time he would Diſcourſe as a man of this Inclination, and at another as a Votary of that, ſo that it was Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to aſſign him to any one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Humour; and indeed in that (if any thing) was his Perfection, for being made up of a great many unprofitable things, they were the more Grateful that they never ſtood a juſt Conſideration; in ſhort, he was what it is Impoſſible to Expreſs without ſo many words, as would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confound than Compleat a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter; and it would be to draw him in ſo many Unlike and Diſproportionable parts, that the ſight muſt be Monſtrous. How <hi>Altophel</hi> followed his firſt Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is eaſily Imagined, and he that had been ſo angry with <hi>Astraea,</hi> was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Speak agreeable things to a Stranger, but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> talked for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and <hi>Altophel</hi> too, and that with a great deal or Confidence and Liberty; the Company they had fallen into (though it was very Modeſt) yet it was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38018:10"/>Capable of Underſtanding all things of good Sence that were Propoſed to them: The firſt Subject that <hi>Rhoderick</hi> fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was Love, as indeed the ſight of any thing that is Handſome, in a moment Inſpires them with that Theme; but his ill way of Speaking on it, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſagreeable to the Company; thoſe who poſſeſt any meaſures of Beauty, and that well underſtand what they own, cannot but eſteem it an Affront to ſee it Defloured by the moſt Laſcivious and Rude diſcourſes; our Beautiful ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers knew themſelves ſo well, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they were Importuned by ſo Wild an Entertainment which had nothing in it but an account of the ill Lives of thoſe who had been unfortunately happy in the beſt Gifts of Nature; he diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them on the Intrigues of great Ladies, he acquainted them with the new Songs, and the freſheſt Adventures of the Town, he communicated to them all the Intereſts, Dependencies, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, of the moſt conſiderable Beauties: But he did it in Terms ſo Wild, and ſo full of Lightneſs, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an ill Divertiſement to them, and they could not but tell him that he loſt all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38018:11"/>that diſcourſe which he uſed to thoſe who neither Admired nor underſtood it; and that he would do them a Favour to change the Subject to ſome thing more Innocent and more agreeable. <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> though not at all out of Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, yet found himſelf at a Loſs, becauſe he had never been uſed to ſay any thing elſe to a Woman but on the Obſcene occaſions of Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel,</hi> though he was of a Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city good enough, yet the great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with which his Friend Diſcourſed, wholly Diſcouraged him from mingling in the Converſation; when <hi>Rhoderick</hi> had got him alone, he very freely Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to him his Opinion of their Female company, and told him that without doubt they were Ladies of a great deal of Kindneſs, only that they uſed thoſe ſeeming Severities to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe their Inclinations, and to bring on the Courtſhip: And you ſhall ſee <hi>Altophel,</hi> ſaid he, that I will enjoy one or both of them before we have ended our Journey. <hi>Altophel,</hi> who did not understand the Nature of ſuch Perſons, and by what Figure they Diſcourſed, was Surprised at the great Sufficiency
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38018:11"/>of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and could believe no Vertue Impregnable if that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo powerful, ſhould at laſt yield to the Aſſault of a Stranger: all along their Travel, and at their Inns <hi>Altophel</hi> could ſee no alteration in the Behaviour of the Ladies, nor find that they Liſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any greater pleaſure to the wild Diſcourſes of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> but whatever Impreſſions they took (though they were unknown to <hi>Altophel</hi>) yet thoſe which his Friend Communicated to him were very ſtrange, for he told him that he had received Favours from both of them in private, and he once or twice in the Night went out of his Bed on an appointment, I think we may without any Injuſtice be of the Opinion, that there was nothing in all this but the Vanity and the Affectation of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and though ſome may think it ſtrange that Gentlemen chooſe ſo wild a Pleaſure, as to Traduce that Vertue which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not overcome, and to make thoſe Whores by their Diſcourſes, whom their Practices could never Vanquiſh; yet theſe things are eaſily believed by a moments Conſideration: The <hi>Loves</hi> of that Nature are now the moſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38018:12"/>and the greateſt pieces of Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and it is not at all ſtrange, that Vain-Glorious and Frollick youth ſhould Create thoſe Triumphs to it ſelf, which it finds to be ſo much Eſteemed and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued. We ſee in other things how much men, for their own Phancies, practiſe a prodigious Lying, and it is not to be queſtioned but that they will take the ſame Liberty in thoſe Subjects which afford the moſt Fame and Reputation. It is an Unhappineſs, that a general Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice has Endear'd the Temptations to a Fault ſo Pernicious and Inglorious, not only Robbing the Innocent of a juſt Reputation, which they ſo carefully have ſought to maintain, but alſo doing them conſiderable Injuries, either among their Friends, or with thoſe Perſons where their moſt near Concernments lie; there are none who well underſtand themſelves, but above all things Value an unblemiſht Fame; and nothing is ſo conſiderable a Loſs to a Woman, as the Poſſeſſion and the Opinion of her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and thoſe who attempt really to Deprive them of that Endowment, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid the Cenſure of being Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, but thoſe who Create the Grime
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38018:12"/>for them and divulge it, are much more Barbarous: But of this we may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was not the firſt Perſon who had Contracted a Guilt of this Nature, and that he had took it from a Thouſand Preſidents of thoſe who were his firſt Inſtructors. After theſe things had been told to <hi>Altophel,</hi> he looked on his Company with other apprehenſions, all their Coldneſs he Interpreted as an Art to diſguiſe their Inclinations, but the leaſt ſhew of Civility became Scandalous to him; ſo apt is a received Opinion to make us Interpret all things by it, and the actions of the moſt Innocent vertue require to their advantage a Candid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; this is certain, there is that ill in every Perſon as to make them too apt to believe all things that are told to the diſadvantage of others, and thoſe have a great deal of Charity and good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture about them that never admit into their Breſts any belief to the prejudice of another; it were to be wiſht, that the World would let fall ſuch Unkind and Scandalous practices, but if they will maintain them, it would be ſome Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration if thoſe who are careful of their own Vertue, would ſtop their Ears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38018:13"/>the ill Reports which are Divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the Infamy of others. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in an Age ſo generally Corrupt, there is a neceſſity that thoſe who abhor to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle in the common Vices, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſufficient ſtock of ill Nature to help them from thoſe Violences they are ſubject to by Civility. There was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more remarkable in this Journey but that our Travellers lying upon the Road on a Sunday, <hi>Altophel</hi> roſe early to go himſelf to the Church, and to wait upon the Ladies thither, but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> Laughed at his <hi>Nothern</hi> Devotion, and told him that neither Piety nor good Breeding were conſiderations great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to contradict the Practice of the moſt eminent Wits, who have by their Oppoſition turn'd the Stream from the Temple to the Theatre; thither you muſt go <hi>Altophel,</hi> to Learn Vertue and Morality, and you will be a Heretick amongſt us if you practiſe theſe things <hi>Altophel</hi> told him, that for that Morning he would be Religious, and he would be Civil; and that to Oblige him to a new Faith, required more arguments that he was at Leiſure to receive at that time when they came Home, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38018:13"/>ready and prepared to Rally with the Ladies and the Squire on account of their Devotion; but though he expreſſed an Extravagant Haughtineſs whilſt, he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon himſelf as an Example conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough to contradict all they could Urge for their Practice, yet it did not produce any other Effects than to make them abhor his Self conceited Impiety. When they came to the Town they all diſperſed themſelves to their ſeveral Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſiors, <hi>Altophels</hi> Friend was now to be the whole diſpoſer of him; for he was ſo unexperienc'd in that place, that it was neceſſary he ſhould ſubmit to the Conduct of a man that underſtood all things in it; <hi>Altophels</hi> Equipage was a little Scandalous for the Town, for though he was Valued in the Country by thoſe that knew where his <hi>Paternal Mannors</hi> lay, and how much he would have <hi>per annum,</hi> yet in the City where they judge all things by appearance, he was like to find no more Reſpect than what his outſide procured him, except his Friend had always like a Herald proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him the Heir to ſuch an Eſtate; <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> was at firſt ſomething at a Loſs to Manage his Habiliments, and to do thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38018:14"/>things that might be agreeable to ſo much Bravery as thoſe Men of Art had put on him; a young Gentleman ſo Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and Unpractiſed in the Modes of the Town, could not but be out of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in his firſt Traverſes, and it was a Divertiſement to <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and the Company he carried him into, to ſee the untoward Behaviour of <hi>Altophel;</hi> the Pleaſure was not diſagreeable to them, becauſe of that Affectation with which they behold any man in thoſe Predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they carried him to Court, to the Plays, to the Park and the Mulber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-Garden; and now <hi>Altophel,</hi> inſtead of one, had a whole <hi>Legion</hi> of <hi>Tutors;</hi> one would complain, as they carried him along, that his Hat was turn'd up on the wrong ſide, another that his Perruke had not the grand Buckle, a third would put his Sword from his Pocket, ſo that <hi>Altophel</hi> was perpetually alarm'd to adjuſt ſomething or other about him: He had Learned to Daunce in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but for want of aſſurance he could not Walk very Gracefully, eſpecially not in the grand Slur, which they told him he muſt by all means Learn; but theſe ſleight things were not like to make the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38018:14"/>Squire any great Proficient, nor Faſhion him to that Character they deſired to enter him in. How far in the Surprizes of all theſe Novelties and Bravery, he forgot his faithful <hi>Astraea;</hi> is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per now to determine: His anger had ſet that Paſſion into ſo Remote a Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Soul, from whence all theſe fine things kept it from coming back to its firſt Poſſeſſion; and we will believe it pardonable in a Youth to give himſelf up to the admiration of thoſe Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to which he was ſo much a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> who was now his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, had ſo much Buſineſs of his own which conſiſted of Love and Play, that he was not always at leiſure to give Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to <hi>Altophel,</hi> and indeed he was a Perſon very much given to Gaming, and having by it ſpent a conſiderable fortune, he became a Penſioner to that Crime he had been Ruin'd by; they Lay toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a little after they had been in Town, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> having been abroad, came Home one Morning very early, having (as appeared afterward) loſt all his Revenue the Night before; <hi>Altophel</hi> roſe from him (according to his <hi>Northern</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:38018:15"/>Induſtry) and thought it Civil to let him lie till Noon, having been deprived of his Nights repoſe; but when Twelve a Clock came, he thought it not ill Manners to call him up, that they might look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Dinner; but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> civily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that he was much Indiſpoſed, and could not eat any thing that day, and therefore deſired of the Squire that he would take care of himſelf till the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: When that came, and <hi>Altophel</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Home, he found his Friend in the ſame condition he had left him; he made a great many of his Innocent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries concerning his Indiſpoſition, and asked him whether he would have a Doctor, or any of his Friends ſent for; <hi>Rhoderick</hi> Swore at that propoſal, and told him that he was not a Man ſubject to thoſe Phancies, but that ſince he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared really to eſteem him, he would Communicate to him what was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his keeping his Bed: He told him that the Night before he had been deeply engaged in Play, and that he had Loſt Three Hundred Pounds, which was all the Stock he had by him, that the Quarter-day was a little too Remote, and that till then he ſhould be in ſome neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38018:15"/>for Money, he did not acquaint <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> with theſe things to be pittied by him, but to have his aſſiſtance; which he had thus contrived, that this young Gentleman ſhould be a Security with him for Two Hundred Pounds, which he would take up at extravagant Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt for Three Months. <hi>Altophel</hi> was too Innocent and Modeſt to deny him, and accordingly became Bound with him for ſo much Money, which ſet him up again in his old Trade, he had at firſt that good Judgment that he never took <hi>Altophel</hi> with him, but to places of ſome Reputation; and when he did any ill thing, he avoided the cenſure of the Squire, though he afterwards fell into it by an innumerable company of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. <hi>Altophel</hi> uſually left him about Ten of the Clock at night, and how he ſpent his time after that, he never failed to Communicate to him, when he came Home; though without doubt, what ever his Adventures were, he was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that they ſhould appear great and Important: Sometimes he would tell him that he had won Two Hundred pounds, and at another that he had loſt as much, becauſe a perpetual good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38018:16"/>would have created a ſuſpition of being Fabulous; ſometimes he would ſay that he had been all night with a Female Perſon of Honour, and at another, that he had been entertained by ſome Noble mans Miſtreſs: Play and Love compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all his Exploits. What good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or what bad he had in the firſt, <hi>Altophel</hi> underſtood not in ſome time, but he was much Incommoded with his ill Succeſs in the latter; for he happen'd to get a very great Clap, which made him but ill Company to <hi>Altophel;</hi> he ſaid he got it of a very great Lady, but that could not render him leſs Inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Country Squire, who had never before Encountred any of thoſe Tragick pieces of Gallantry; he was for ſome time Obliged to ſtay at Home, where beſides his Indiſpoſition, he was a Perſon the moſt Dull and Tireſome in the World, having nothing of that Vivaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Care which attended him abroad: He ſat drooping over a Play-Book, <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandra,</hi> or <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and in a diſmal Night-Gown Swore extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly at his Miſ-fortune: <hi>Altophel</hi> told him one day, that of all the Pleaſures of the Town he thought the Women
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38018:16"/>the moſt Pernicious, becauſe they are paid ſo dear for in ſuch cruel Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> in all his Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity would not let that paſs for a ſound Perſwaſion, but told him that the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Love were ſo perpetual, that a few days Torment were too Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable to be an Impediment to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging of them, that it was the Fate of all to ſuffer ſuch things, and that the commonneſs of the Diſaſter had made it leſs Formidable, that no man of any Generoſity ſhould ſcruple to ſuffer what the moſt Delicate and the moſt Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Women frequently endure, and that a Diſeaſe which wracks Creatures ſo ſweet and tender, ought to be Mockt at by the Reſolution of a more enduring Sex; but all theſe raiſed Diſcourſes could not appear good Philoſophy to <hi>Altophel,</hi> who thought it better to be ſpared from a Partnerſhip with the moſt Beautiful in ſuch ſort of Sufferings. But that which was the moſt Irkſome to <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> in his preſent Durance, was the being Confined from thoſe Encounters that were his perpetual Buſineſs and Pleaſure: He was often viſited by his Friends, and ſometimes by thoſe of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38018:17"/>Female Sex; <hi>Altophel</hi> was an uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon to judge of their Quality by their Deportment and Diſcourſes, for he found that the beſt Ladies in his Country Talk'd not by ſo Refined a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure as they did; but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> when they were gone, ever ſupplied the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of his Knowledge by telling him that they were ſuch and ſuch great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and Wives to Perſons of conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reputation; the Youth could not but admire at their Humility and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of their Kindneſs, to make Viſits to a young Gentleman in thoſe Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but what ever he might force <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> to believe, we are at Liberty to imagine them ſuch on whom <hi>Rhoderick</hi> beſtowed wrong Characters, and that Perſons of ſuch Qualities better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelves than to go beyond their Decorum by mean and contrary Actions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38018:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Trappan with two Whores.</head>
            <p>DUring this time of <hi>Rhodercks</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, <hi>Altophel</hi> often ſtraggled abroad by himſelf; he was a Perſon not Unhanſome, nor at that time ill Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and he was one day walking in a Place where Perſons of different Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours uſe to Reſort, and we may Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he walked with his natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Baſhfulneſs, which could not but make him taken Notice of by thoſe who perfectly underſtand the way of the Town, and that through all Dreſſes know a man of Faſhion: Two very fine Ladies, perceiving <hi>Altophel</hi> to be a Novice by his Gate and the Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about of his Head, came Ruſhing by him, and one of them by the hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſhock turn'd him about; had they not ſet him in a right poſture
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38018:18"/>to look after them, their appearance it ſelf was too Conſiderable not to attract the Eyes of our admiring Youth; when he was conſidering them, one of them pulled off her Maſque half-way, and ſhewed him thoſe things which ſatisfied him that ſhe cruelly concealed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of a very beautiful Face: <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> turning again to purſue his walk, began to conſider his own Merit, and to take a better account of it by a careful Survey of his Proportion. Our Self-love, and Flattery are ſuch damnable Qualities, that we will ever be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting all things to our own Advantage, and it is impoſſible for our judgment to ſerve us againſt them; <hi>Altophel</hi> could not but think that his appearance had Charmed thoſe Ladies, and he was Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make the utmoſt of his good Fortune; the end of the Walk and his own Vanity obliged him to come back, and ſo did the Ladies, reſolving to do all things that they could with this Baſhful young Gentleman; and as they came up again to him, a Gentleman walking on the other hand, juſt as they pull'd off their Maſques, ſaid to another, his Companion, there goes my Lady <hi>P.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38018:18"/>Altophel</hi> by that word heightned the good Opinion which he had conceived of himſelf, and thought, if they ſhould Oblige him any further to wait upon them, that he might very well truſt himſelf in ſuch good Company; it was likely the Surpriſed Youth forgot his Diſtreſſed Friend at Home, who lay Roaring like a Cannon with his inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Clap: When a Temptation is ready to ſeize us, we ſeldom have thoſe Conſiderations about us which are neceſſary to make us ſtrong enough to Repulſe it; the appearance of two La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whom Art and Nature had made extraordinary, with their Faſhion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Youth, might well cauſe him to forget what he would at another time have better remembred; the next turn they took they preſented themſelves juſt before <hi>Altophel,</hi> who muſt have Charg'd through them if he had vanquiſht that Oppoſition; but he had not Courage enough for ſuch an Enterprise, and therefore only Drew up in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner before them. You will imagine that he accoſted them with no very good Grace, and though he was a Perſon of Sence enough, and of a good Behaviour
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38018:19"/>where he had time to recover his aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but his ſmall Experience in thoſe Matters, together with the Surprize he he was in, might make him more Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dextrous than he uſed to be; what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements he made them I never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and though I am apt to believe they were not very good ones, yet the Ladies without doubt accepted of them, having other Buſineſs with him: In ſhort, the Squire was planted betwixt them, and each of them had ſeized him by the hand, they had ſo Charmingly bound him to his good Behaviour, that he was willing to be lead any whither by them; and he could not in thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments believe that the moſt Luſcious Liberty was comparable to ſo ſweet a Confinement. When they came to the place where the Coaches ſtood, ſhe whom we may imagine to be my Lady <hi>P.</hi> appeared a little angry that her Coach was not there, but the other made an Excuſe for the negligence of the Coach-man, and <hi>Altophel</hi> put them both into a Hackney. Whether they would car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him he could not ſuddenly think, but what pleaſant Idaeas he ſhaped to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf we may eaſily Imagine, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38018:19"/>his Youth and his Innocence in theſe Matters; at laſt they came to a place very well known, and he had (by what means he knew not) a very Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Supper brought up; they did (doubtleſs) entertain the Squire in a more extraordinary manner than he had ever been before, and taught him thoſe things to which he had been wholly a ſtranger: at the end of the Supper, another Lady came up, and in a great deal of Confuſſion told them, that Sir <hi>P.</hi> and Sir <hi>N.</hi> were below; which made the Ladies appear much diſtracted: <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> addreſſed himſelf to them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know what Conſideration they had for thoſe Gentlemen which the Lady had told them of; they are, ſaid the Ladies, ſuch Perſons whom, becauſe we love not, we have reaſon to fear; and by this account you will readily Imagine who they muſt be: They firſt propoſed the putting <hi>Altophel</hi> behind the Hangings, and the Squire was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to abſcond, but one of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies expreſſed her Opinion contrary to that Reſolution, and told them, that it was better to go down and Encounter them below, than to permit them to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38018:20"/>ravage in a place where they had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to preſerve a Perſon whom they eſteemed; this was approved of by them all, they returned no more after they diſappeared, and a Bill, ſomething larger than a Taylors, was brought up to <hi>Altophel;</hi> he asked for his beautiful Company, and it was anſwered him that they were gone, and that they had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered That to be brought him; the ſume was too Extravagant that the young Squire was not furniſhed for the diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of it, he had not the way of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoring the Houſe, nor any Slight to bring himſelf off from ſo Prodigious a Reckoning; he was ſo little known in the Inn that he could not ſend for any to Bail him, and ſo he ſtaid very willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly till the Morning, he knew it was in vain to ſend for <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> for if it had been to ſave his Life he could not have come to his Reſcue; but when day-light appeared, the Houſe (being better pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in thoſe things than <hi>Altophel</hi> was told him that one ſhould wait upon him to his Lodgings and receive the Money there, which he was unwilling to do becauſe then all muſt be Diſcovered to <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> which he was a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38018:20"/>at, but neceſſity obliged him to do a thing much to his Regret, and having a Waiter at his Heels inſtead of a Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he went Home and Diſcharged the Reckoning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> could not diſſemble this ill adventure from his Friend, to whom it appeared extreamly pleaſant, and he took an occaſion from the Dulneſs of the Squire to read him a Lecture to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of his Gravity: What think you now Sir, ſaid he to <hi>Altophel,</hi> of the Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable Charms of the Women in this Town? Without doubt you have as little Reſolution as any man, when the Temptation comes upon you; beſides, there is a difference betwixt us two, for you have your Country Modeſty left, to defend you againſt thoſe aſſaults that are too bold and hardy upon you, but our perpetual Liberty and Confidence renders all things Modeſt and eaſie to us. <hi>Altophel</hi> could only Gape and Look ſcurvily at this Diſcourſe, and he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be no more the Subject of it, but after-moments ſhewed him the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe Reſolutions, for no ſooner had they done talking, but a letter came to <hi>Altophel</hi> from one of the Ladies he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38018:21"/>had been with the night before, and who had got him Dog'd home, in which he found a long Excuſe for leaving him in that manner, which was occaſioned by the unhappy coming of their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; but that they had now contrived a perfect Security from all ſuch Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, by being at the Lodgings of a Lady who was their Confident, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they deſired him to come in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, that they may give him reaſon to entertain better thoughts of them than he could receive from the adventure of the laſt Night.</p>
            <p>This Note gave <hi>Altophel</hi> ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and he readily caſhiered all thoſe hard Opinions he had conceived of the Ladies for the late affront. He went in the Evening to the place where they had appointed to meet him, and where he found them ſo Illuſtrious, as to be capable of Melting down a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Hearts more Obdurate than that of the poor Squire; at the firſt coming he plaid at Cards with them, where all the Mony that they won of him he reckoned he had loſt in Gallantry, becauſe <hi>Ovid,</hi> who was a very great Author with him, had Inſtructed him ever to looſe to that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38018:21"/>Sek: There was, Three Ladies to one <hi>Altophel;</hi> whereas, if there had been Thee <hi>Altophels</hi> to one Lady, yet the Squires would have found themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-match'd; they drank Wine whilſt they plaid, to make their Game more chearful, but always when it came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to <hi>Altophel</hi> there was ſomething in the Glaſs, ſo pernicious, that he not only loſt his Senſe and Underſtanding, but grew very Sick at his Stomach; which he could not but diſcover to his Company, the Ladies appeared ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly compaſſionate of him, and though he expreſſed a Rambling deſire to be carried Home to his Lodgings, yet it was Impoſſible for him to overcome the Officiouſneſs with which the Ladies undreſſed him for Bed, where, after they had committed him to his Repoſe, and done a great many wanton things with him (which out of reſpect to that Sex we are willing to Omit) they left him nothing but his. Shirt, and an incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Underſtanding to bear him through ſo perplexing a Labyrinth. In the Morning he found himſelf very well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but no one came to give him the Good-morrow, nor preſent him with a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38018:22"/>kind Draught to ſettle his diſordered Stomach, at laſt he reſolved to pardon them that Neglect, and to Riſe by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; but when he came to look for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Clothes, he could find nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Shooes, of what he had worn the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before, this made him Rage extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly, and to go about in his Shirt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enquire after his Habiliments, of whom ſoever he met: at laſt a Virgin appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our Knight Errant, but the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhe gave him of thoſe Raviſhed he ſought, was very unpleaſing; ſo ſhe told him that they had that Night gone away, and took their things with them, telling her Maſter that their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen who lay in their Lodgings that night would Satisfie him for that time they had been in his Houſe: The Maid held this Conference with ſome niceneſs, becauſe of the naked condition of <hi>Altophel,</hi> and ſhe told him that ſhe would ſend he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maſter to him; with which he retired again to his Bed, where Summing up all the Underſtanding he had, he thought there was no other way left but to have it paſs for a Frolick acted by Ladies that were a Kin to him: When the owner of the Houſe came up, he told him he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38018:22"/>had Premeditated; at which the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman could not but Laugh; he asked him how much they were in arrear for their Lodgings, but he was told of ſo round a Sum, that he was like to have ſpoileed his own Deſign of letting it paſs for a Frolick, by the Rage he fell into at the hearing of it; but there was no other way but to ſend for his Footman, to bring his old Clothes and his Money, which he did, and took his leave of the Landlord, who deſired him to preſent his Service to thoſe merry Ladies.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Altophel</hi> came home to <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> he asked him where he had been that night in Maſquerade, and with whom he had truſted his Clothes? <hi>Altophel</hi> only replied that his new Sute had come by a Miſchance, and that he muſt have another made. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ſuſpecting ſomething of the truth, would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any further about it, but ſpoke to him of other things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38018:23"/>
            <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Maſquerade.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat night there was to be a great Ball at a Perſons of Quality, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome Gentlemen that came to ſee <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> invited <hi>Altophel</hi> to go along with them in Maſquerade. <hi>Altophel</hi> took upon him the Habit, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, reſolving to keep himſelf as Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of all Adventures, as he was unknown to all the World in that Dreſs; but our Reſolutions are vain, whilſt we take no care to mortifie that Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we carry about us. To have done a Thouſand fooliſh things. will not Ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us to reſiſt the next occaſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking ſome Courſe with our Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and applying effectual Remedies to them: That Philoſophy which admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht us <hi>to know our ſelves,</hi> directed us aright to the Principles of Good and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38018:23"/>Evil, which have ever their Fountains in our own Breſts. <hi>Altophel</hi> by two ſmart Encounters, was Taught the Danger of having any thing to do with the Town Women, but he received no Benefit from that Experience, whilſt he only condemned the Adventures, and acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Amours</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Ball they went to this night was the firſt which our Youth had ſeen, and it was one of the moſt Magnificent which had ever been in the Town, where appeared an Infinite number of Ladies, ſo Admirably and yet ſo antickly Dreſſed, who cunningly kept thoſe Faces in Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcade, to whoſe Cruelties the Dreſs and the meen were the Allurers. <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> having a handſome Face, and being altogether a Stranger, was ever putting off his Maſque, by which he was known to the Ladies that had ſo ill Treated him the night before; they Communicated all things concerning him to another ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine Lady, who reſolved to make uſe of the Occaſion, and taking a fit time to do it, ſhe came up to <hi>Altophel,</hi> and Beckoning him to a Window, her appearance obliged him to follow her; ſhe was admirably Dreſſed, and had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38018:24"/>her a great quantity of Jewels, which were more Illuſtrious in the Ecclipſe of her Beauty that was then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Maſque. You will (ſaid ſhe) have a great deal of reaſon to think me very good Natur'd, that I ſhould enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this Converſation with you after the affront of the laſt night; but I have not that Value for any of your Quality as to be angry with you, ſince we never take the pains to be Reveng'd on any but thoſe we have eſteemed. <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph</hi> continued ſhe, I know I am not the firſt with whoſe Civility you have taken the Liberty to Divert your ſelf, an attempt which my Birth and Quality might have Deterr'd you from, though my Vertue makes me uncapable of uſing that Revenge which others practiſe on the ſame Occaſion (a conſideration which made you think your ſelf Secure in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting me) but I will take that which ſhall be agreeable to my own humour, which is, not to trouble my thoughts with the remembrance of your folly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> was amazed at this diſcourſe, and to find himſelf charged with that Crime by a Perſon whom he thought ſo very conſiderable; he often opened
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38018:24"/>his Mouth to have Interrupted her, but the vehemency with which ſhe expreſſed her ſelf, ever prevented him when he would have ſpoken, and he was the more willingly Silenced becauſe of the deſire he had to know all the Intrigue; but at laſt when ſhe ſaid nothing, and was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, he told her that ſhe had miſtaken the Perſon whom ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to Chaſtiſe, but that ſhe had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected her anger to a man whoſe Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Town might ſecure her from all Suſpitions, that he would do her a prejudice by what ſhe had declared to him; the angry Lady ſeemed Surprized at the Errors ſhe committed, and told <hi>Altophel</hi> that ſhe was very ſorry ſhe had accuſed an Innocent Perſon with any things ſhe had Expreſſed in her anger, but that though he extreamly reſembled a very ill man, yet ſhe hoped his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities were very unlike to his, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in this, not to do her an Injury by Divulging any thing ſhe had Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him of thoſe Reſentments ſhe had againſt another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> could not but make her a Thouſand Complements, and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that great Care he would have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38018:25"/>of a ſecret which a Perſon of her appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance had committed to him, and that he ſhould be proud of carrying about him any thing that was conſiderable with ſo divine a Perſon. The wily <hi>Maſquera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> found theſe Diſcourſes very agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and being a Lady, beſides of a good Wit, alſo the Owner of a Face that the moſt Stoical could never look upon with Indifference, ſhe ſhewed it to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> with this addreſs: Becauſe ſome of my Affairs are by accident fallen into your hands, you ſhall ſee how conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a proof I will give you of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in your Generoſity, by the ſight of a Face that will tell you who I am, and from whom you have received a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. <hi>Altophel,</hi> at the ſight of her Face and the greatneſs of her Looks, found a Reverence in his Soul for her Beauty and Appearance, and he expreſſed it to her in as good Terms as he could; I ſhall expect this from you, continued ſhe, that you give me the ſame Knowledge of a man to whom I have uſed this Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by the ſight of your Face; which obliged him preſently to put off his Maſque, with this Diſcourſe: I ſhall ſhew you a Face, Madam, of which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38018:25"/>you have no Knowledge, for I am alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a Stranger in this Town. I am pleaſed, replied ſhe, to ſee a Face which as I eſteem for its Appearance, ſo I wholly Ignore it. The little Knowledge which you have in the Town is the greater Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of your Juſtice, not having had time to learn thoſe ill Qualities by which young Gentlemen uſually De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch it; after all this which has paſt betwixt us, I am reſolved to have you this night for my Maſquerader; after which they conſorted together, going from one Room to another, where the Lady ſoiled not to ſpeak the moſt charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pleaſing things to <hi>Altophel;</hi> and ſhe did with a great deal of Freedome let him know ſo much concerning her, as might oblige his Friendſhip; the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was one of the beſt Habited in the Room, which cauſed ſeveral of the Company to come up to her, which ſhe handſomely ſhun'd, and only deſigned to draw <hi>Altophel</hi> after her by her Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and her Obliging faſhion, which could not but be Extraordinary pleaſing to the Youth, to ſee himſelf preferr'd before all others by ſo fine a Lady. She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved her ſelf with ſo Charming an
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38018:26"/>Inſenſibility at all things that were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting in the Ball; that the Squire was Confounded with the Pleaſure he felt, by Imagining that her thoughts were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implied in what Concern'd himſelf. He endeavoured to do that that might appear Gallant, and ſhe received all his Actions with ſo pretty a Contentment; as made him Proud and Charmed in the doing of them; at the end of the Ball ſhe went away with her Company, and civilly took her Leave of <hi>Altophel.</hi> He beg'd the knowledge of her Name, but ſhe told him that was not neceſſary; but yet ſhe would ſo far Comply with his Curioſity as to give him the Sign by which he ſhould know her in the Park the next Evening: When ſhe was gone the Squire went to find out his Friends, and he met them making Love to ſeveral Ladies, when the Morning came that they were to be gone, they obliged <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> to go Home with them, to be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed in their Lodgings, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to, and took part of their Repoſe. When they were Ready and going out one of thoſe Gentlemen, pulling his Handkerchiff out of his Pocket, drop a Letter; which had on it a Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38018:26"/>for the other Gentleman that was with them, who happen'd to ſnatch it up, and ſeeing his Name upon it, grew very angry with his Companion, for meddling with thoſe Letters that were directed to him: But the other Swore that he knew not how it came there, but that he believed it was put into his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, by ſome Lady in Maſquerade, who had miſtaken his Name, but the other would not be deprived of a Paper which had ſo great a right to as a Direction, nor would the other Reſign a Letter that he had in his Poſſeſſion: In this fury <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> was Obliged to Moderate betwixt them, and to propoſe that the Letter might be Read by conſent in the Hearing of both, which they at laſt agreed to, and one of them ſnatched it open to read it, the beginning of the Letter Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd a great deal of Kindneſs, and the moſt generous Declarations of a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſome Gentleman who had Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Writer in Maſquerade. At the end of every amorous Sentence, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals inflamed themſelves to a new Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, each of them avowing that they had the night before made Love to a Perſon of Quality, and it muſt come from the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38018:27"/>ſame Lady they had Courted, becauſe it was exactly a <hi>Repartee</hi> to thoſe things they had ſpoken; for they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but that the VVriter was a Lady of very great Account: Every Line that was read appeared to have more and more Dearneſs in it, which encreaſed the Paſſion, the Animoſity, and Jealouſie of the Gallants; at laſt there was the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Appointment at a place not far off, at which the Lovers grew ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, that one of them took up his Sword to be gone; Vowing that if the other followed him he would Oblige him to diſpute that Felicity; the other Swore as faſt, and Threatned the ſame things if he endeavour'd to prevent him of a Joy which was Deſign'd him, by the Lady: Here they left off Reading, and were preparing like two <hi>Racers</hi> in <hi>Olympia,</hi> to win the Lady by the beſt Footmanſhip, but <hi>Altophel</hi> deſired them to Read out the Letter before they went, and not to go Charg'd with half the Sentiments of ſo divine a Perſon; which with much difficulty, and with a prepared Animoſity they agreed to do; when, having read ſome more of the kind Expreſſions, they at laſt came to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38018:27"/>the end, which was in theſe Terms: That though the Perſon who writ it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Exchange,</hi> yet that could not diſcourage her at the Liberty ſhe took to expreſs a real Kindneſs for ſo accompliſht a Gentleman: This conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in a moment cooled the Animoſity of the Rivals, and looking upon each other very calmly, <hi>Altophel</hi> at laſt broke the ſilence by a loud Laughter, which much encreaſed the ſimplicity of his Friends, who then began to diſown the Letter with as much earneſtneſs as they had formerly made a claim to it, each averring that it did not belong to him. After the Mirth was over, they went all to <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> where having told him the Adventure, he at laſt owned himſelf to be the Contriver of it. They Dined together, and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> who was now in a condition to go abroad, propoſed to the Company to go to the Play, but <hi>Altophel</hi> excuſed himſelf, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome Buſineſs which he had: <hi>Rhoderick</hi> told him in Jeſt, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he had a deſign to go and meet the Perſon who wrote the Letter, but he hoped he would not amuſe himſelf with ſuch mean Loves, ſince (if he would
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38018:28"/>be amorous) he could better provide him of a Court. <hi>Altophel</hi> diſowned all ſuch Deſigns, though he knew himſelf a going to a greater Aſſignation than he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved <hi>Rhoderick</hi> could provide for him; he went to the Park as Country Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men uſe to go to the Play, two hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning, where the want of Company was no Regret to him, for he had ſo much in his thoughts that he would have overlookt the beſt Divertiſements had he found them at that time. <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> walked a great while, and with as much Impatience as Love and Curioſity could Inſpire him with; but time, that never fails our longeſt Expectation, at laſt brough the Hour in which <hi>Altophel</hi> was to receive a Felicity he ſo much Long'd for, but it paſſed over without being propitious to the Squire: He could not, amongſt all the fair Ladies that were walking there that Evening, ſee any thing that could give him the knowledge of her he ſought; he ſtaied the laſt of all the Company, and went away with a Soul as Gloomy as that Night which ſent him Home; but the Lady whom he was to have ſeen, though ſhe appeared not to him, yet ſhe did
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38018:28"/>not forget him; for as he was going Home to his Lodgings, one came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind and gave him a Note in which he found an Excuſe for hot being there, and an aſſurance that he might receive that Satisfaction (if it would be any to him) in another place. The next Evening thither he went, and there he found that Lady, whoſe Beauty was too Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able not to do all things that belong'd to the Subduing of <hi>Altophel:</hi> Here he ſaw her, and fed his Soul with a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fuel, but it was Impoſſible for him to approach Her, which Inflamed the Ardour of the Youth, whilſt he was kept at a Bay; ſhe went away with her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and took with her the Soul and Paſſion of <hi>Altophel;</hi> the diſ-ſpirited Youth ſtragled after her, being rather Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by his Love than any Sence he had left to purſue a Perſon who had done him ſo much Miſchief: The Coach had her at laſt from his ſight, but her Idea was left in his Breſt, with all the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of a Tyrannick Beauty. He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times meaſured the Traverſe, at the end of which he had left her, and ſpent his beſt Judgment on the Adventure; he concluded that either it was ſent him by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38018:29"/>Chance, which does Inaccountable things or elſe was the effect of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit his own Modeſty would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to take a juſt account of. He remembred that he had once been ill Treated by Ladies of a great Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but this had in it too much Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditation, and length of Circumſtance to be of that Nature; however, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſatisfie his Curioſity ſo far as to purſue it, till it grew of ill Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to him; ſo apt are we to Drill our ſelves into Pernicious actions; and to Fool with our own underſtandings. When any Encounter pleaſes us, and our Senſe ſuggeſts an Inconvenience to be in it, 'tis ſtrange to ſee how hard we Labour to take off from our Appetites all the Arreſts of our Underſtandings, to which we blindly become the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for all their Extravagance. <hi>Altophel,</hi> when he had done all things to ſatisfie himſelf that this was a happy Adventure, went home-wards to his Lodgings, and by the way met with an Extraordinary appearance, the ſight of which Entertained him at once with an extraordinary Flame, and caught him by the Ears with admirable Muſick,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38018:29"/>made him at firſt imagine it to be <hi>Pluto</hi> going with <hi>Proſerpine</hi> in Maſquerade; but when he came near, he ſaw in a Coach the Figures of Mortal men, and one of them ſo like <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that he believed ſome one with the ſpight of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo</hi> had depainted him in haſte; but <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> (whom it was indeed) though ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Fiddlers and Link-Boys, whilſt he was Mounted like <hi>Phaeton,</hi> and with a Head more giddy than his at the ſight of the proſtrate World, yet call'd out aloud to <hi>Altophel</hi> by his Name, which ſatisfied (a little) the amazed Squire that it was no Apparition, but ſome great piece of Extravagancy; they took him into the Coach and abundantly Lull'd him, and Careſſed him in their Drink, it was in vain for him to ask them whether they were going, for that had been a piece of Gravity inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſo glorious an Elevation. <hi>Altophel</hi> being ſurrounded with ſo much Light and Muſick, and having Company in the Coach that had no Judgment of any thing about them, believed he might run into very ſtrange Conſequences before that Frolick was ended; at laſt the Coach ſtopped at a Houſe whether ſome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38018:30"/>of the Company had directed it: After great Knocking at the Door it was at laſt opened, but the ſight was very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to <hi>Altophel,</hi> who was more ſober than the reſt of the Troop; they charg'd out of one Room into another, and here you might have ſeen one Woman in her Smock, flying like the Wind before her Purſuers whilſt another Tripped it down Stairs with her Petticoat caſt over her Shoulders after the Mode of the <hi>Greek Tunick;</hi> a third appeared at a Chamber-door, Dancing naked to the Muſick that came with <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and which was left below; a fourth got a Pick-a-pack about one of their Necks; which ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perceiving, and being diſpleaſed with the Odneſs of the Spectacle, after he had given her the Correction of a Paedagogue, he took her by the Heels and threw her over the ſhoulder of her <hi>Atlas;</hi> with which ſhe made ſo hideous a Noiſe, that the whole Squadron drew together with their old Chieftain at the head of them, who to animate them to a brave Reſiſtance, threw off her Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments, and with many generous actions Defied their Foes; this was Inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the honour of thoſe Gentlemen,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38018:30"/>and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> who was at the head of them, Charg'd with ſo much Fury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one that was his Oppoſite, that the place being on the Brink of a Praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice, the wily Laſs ſlipping from the Shock, cauſed <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to fall head-long to the bottom of it, he made ſo much Noiſe, that ſeveral of the Enemy who were below, placed in <hi>Ambuſcade,</hi> ruſhed out to make him their Priſoner, and Seizing inſtantly on his <hi>Scemitar</hi> they conveyed him to a place, where (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt) they gave him a Treatment ſuitable to the quality of a true Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier. The reſt of the Company ſeeing <hi>Rhodericks</hi> diſaſter, reſolved to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him in Death or Chains; they Ralli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again, and he that was firſt to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his Fellows by a great Example, run head-long into a Party of Women that ſtood drawn up before him; they opened at the Charge, and one of them catching him in her arms, he vented ſo much Cholorick Fury in her Boſome, that being overcome with the exceſs of his Gallantry, ſhe gave him both Life and Liberty; but the others fell on Pell-mell, and an unconcern'd Spectator might there have ſeen all the Honours,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38018:31"/>and all the Extravagancies of War and Fury. In one place lay an <hi>Hero,</hi> and an <hi>Heroine</hi> ſtraggling for Victory, making uſe of all the Arts of Chivalry; and on another Spot lay another Gallant ſtound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his fall, to whom his gentle Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary uſed all the diligence to bring him again to his Senſes, that he might become an Enemy fit for her Honour. <hi>Altophel</hi> alone, by his refuſing to Engage, and by his Capriciouſneſs, became that wretched Coward whom they made the Subject of their Indignation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; a Select party undertook him, and to ſhew how much they deſpiſed his Forces, they Charg'd him ſtark naked, whilſt one of them beat a Battle on her Kettle-Drums. <hi>Altophel</hi> made no other Defence but to puſh at them with his Legs, which diſhonourable way of Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo Inraged them, that one of them catching him by his Foot threw him backward, whilſt another to bring him to himſelf again (for thoſe cruel <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons</hi> ever affect to keep an Enemy long a Dying) ſquirted <hi>Stuponia</hi> in his face; this ſo ſtartled the Squire, that Leaping up again he overbore thoſe who had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len on him; they were thus breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38018:31"/>animoſity againſt each other, when the coming up of <hi>Rhoderick</hi> put an end to their Fury, he had appeared ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Perſon to his Keepers, that they gave him his Liberty, and only took from him an Engagement inſtantly to March out of their Dominions, without any more acts of Hoſtility; he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly drew off his Party which was brought up by <hi>Altophel,</hi> whoſe Pride to go off unwounded was Inſupportable to ſome of his Enemies, and one of them, to give him a proof of her Indignation, lifting up her <hi>Petronel,</hi> gave him ſo great a Blow as Diſmounted him from the <hi>Rampire,</hi> as he was going to deſcend, he fell upon ſome of his Companions with ſo much weight that they all accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied him in the fall, which made <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> ſo angry, that forgetting what he owed to his Word and Honour, he faced about to Attack them, but <hi>Altophel</hi> knowing their Odds, was more willing to go off with ſome Loſs, than to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard more by a ſecond Ingagement; ſo they all Ruſht out of the Door, and whilſt ſome of them Mounted into the Chariot, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> beſtrid one of the Horſes; they Rode a conſiderable time
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38018:32"/>before they met with any Adventure, at laſt they found the Conſtable at the head of the Watch, who bid them ſtand, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was in great wrath at this Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and made a Signal to the Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Link-Boys to Charge, whilſt he himſelf drew to diſpute their Paſſage, but the Horſe he Rode was ſo Unmana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and Inſenſible, that he in vain dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted through the Thickeſt of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: The Conſtable alſo made a Sign to his men to fall on, which they did very Valiantly, and great things were done for the Unhorſing <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> but he ſat ſo skilfully, and Breath'd ſo much Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity, that the attempt was difficult; there was Light enough to make their Valours diſcernable, and Muſick ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to animate the moſt timorous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. At laſt <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> weary with Reſiſtance, and with doing Prodigious things, fell from his Horſe, which Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged thoſe in the Coach to alight and draw. <hi>Altophel</hi> knowing the Nature of the Encounter; addreſſed himſelf to the Conſtable, deſiring him not to Oppoſe the Watch againſt men that were ſo much in Drink, as his Friends were at that time. Sir, ſaid the Conſtable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:38018:32"/>muſt not ſuffer this Affront in my Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and I muſt take a Correction <hi>ad Terrorem,</hi> and for the good of the Community; if theſe things ſhould be ſuffered, we ſhould not have a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Citizen going Home from his Neighbours Houſe in an Evening, but he would be Aſſaſſinated by ſuch Ruffins; the Truſt which is Committed to me <hi>ex Officio,</hi> is very great, and I muſt make good my Charge though it be with the loſs of my Life; and you, Sir, being found in ill Company at this unſeaſonable Hour, muſt take a part with them in the Demerit of their Fault. <hi>Altophel</hi> ſmiled at the Ridiculous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces of the Officer, and ſo turn'd from him, placing himſelf before <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to keep him from provoking the Fury of the Rabble, but there he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe which proved equal Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to him: <hi>Rhoderick</hi> often Butted againſt him with his Head, whilſt he ſtood an Impediment to his <hi>Carriere,</hi> and the Watch often gave him ſmart Attacks, whilſt they endeavoured to rap <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> behind him; ſo that being perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually Juſtled, he grew angry with his Friend and his Enemies, and drew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38018:33"/>out of the Crowd, which ſoon made all the reſt to be taken Priſoners, and he yielded himſelf for company, as not knowing what elſe to do than to ſee the end of this mad Adventure. When the Conſtable had compleated his Victory, he ordered the Lights to be put out, whilſt the Muſick ceas'd, and all things appeared with the blackneſs and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of a Bloody Defeat. But as the Conſtable was carrying his Priſoners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, there Encountred him by the way a Select number of generous Cavaliers, who being in the ſame Elevation with the Vanquiſht, fell upon the Conſtable and the Watch with great Reſolution; the Change of the Scene was wholly Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, for in a moment all the Muſick ſtruck up for Joy and Victory. The Boys lighted both their Links and their Courages at the welcome Flame of their Reſcuers, and neither on the one hand nor the other, would any that had the leaſt Sparks of Gallantry in his Breſt, looſe that occaſion of acquiring Glory, whilſt in the heat of the Fight, an unhappy accident had like to have cauſed the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of the <hi>Heroes;</hi> for <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and his Friends not well underſtanding
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38018:33"/>this Aſſiſtance, and being ſet at Liberty by the Watch, they Charg'd their Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuers with a great deal of fury, but the Conſtable being in the thickeſt of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> on the one hand and one of the new Troop on the other, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to Shock him ſo violently, as whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Intimidated the Officer, and he haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid down his Arms and fled, which ſtruck a Panick fear into all his Party, who followed his Example. VVhen they were gone, the two Squadrons Charg'd angrily at each other, till <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> putting himſelf betwixt them, made them ſo far underſtand themſelves as to know that they were Friends, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly they embraced, giving the Deſerved and mutual Commendations to each others Valour; they went in a Body till they came to their reſpective Quarters, and there they diſperſed: <hi>Altophel</hi> thought himſelf well delivered of ſo odd an Adventure, and after he had taken ſome Repoſe, he began to think of that amiable Perſon for whom he was ſo Paſſionate the night before; her divine Image preſented it ſelf in ſo many Charms to his Soul, that he vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Sacrifice all his Moments to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38018:34"/>glorious Original; he went Af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternoon with <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to the Play <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after that to the Park, and from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> up to Court, but none of all theſe P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> could ſhew him the Beautiful ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> with whom he had left the moſt conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> able part of his Soul; this diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made him take himſelf out of <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericks</hi> Company when he went upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Deſign, which gave a Suſpition to his Friend, that he was framing an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, and whether he did it to Reſcue the Squire from Committing any groſs Errors, or to make a Divertiſment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſmall Experience; he ſet himſelf to Dog <hi>Altophel</hi> in his Rambles, he found that he much frequented the Park and the Court, and he obſerved him to look very earneſtly in the Faces of all the Ladies, as if he wanted the Lineaments of a Perſon for whom he had a Paſſion: <hi>Rhoderick</hi> who knew all the Town<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing more than to ſee that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whom <hi>Altophel</hi> ſought after in all places; and one Afternoon as they were together at the Play, he perceived the Squire to be diſturb'd at the ſight of a Perſon whom he beheld in one of the Boxes, and he alſo perceived a Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38018:34"/>in her, in looking again upon <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel;</hi> he knew the Lady very well, and he knew her Beauty and her Quality to have been better than her good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he could not but wonder how <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> came to direct his Amorous looks to her, or upon what account ſhe was Induced to have any Conſiderations for him; he reſolved to ſee what was the utmoſt of the Buſineſs, and he intended to carry <hi>Altophel</hi> ſo far in the Intrigue, as to Inſtruct him in what might be for his Advantage: The Squire often look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, and at the Muſick bravely ſet himſelf as a fair Mark for the brignteſt and the moſt piercing Eyes in the world, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> looking on him with a ſmile, ſaid to him: <hi>Altophel,</hi> we will not have you fall in Love with that Lady, becauſe ſhe is one of the moſt extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Town, and we ſhall ſpoil you for a Lover to have your Heart broke in pieces at the firſt time, ſhe is as Conſiderable for her Fortune as ſhe is for her Beauty; I believe you will find it agreeable enough to become her Slave, but you have yet too tender a Breaſt to endure all the Cruelties of Deſpair: Theſe words, though they put <hi>Altophel</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38018:35"/>out of Countenance, yet they Animated him in his amorous Deſign, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the private Intrigues he had with that Lady, were ſufficient to defend him from that deſpair which <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh'd him of: The Lady was not well pleaſed to ſee her Lover with <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> whoſe Knowledge in the Town might Inform him of very ill things, and ſhe therefore reſolved to proceed with more Coldneſs and Circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on in the Buſineſs with <hi>Altophel;</hi> ſhe had Informed her ſelf of his good Fortune, and was willing to do her ſelf a Kindneſs by him if it could be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely brought about; though <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> had taken Notice of theſe things to his Friend, yet he could not forbear from going in Search for that Lady; ſo little is Love capable of being Govern'd by thoſe Rules of Prudence which our Judgment tells us are Neceſſary to be Obſerved. Since <hi>Altophel</hi> proceeded ſo ſeriouſly in the Amour, and made the Lady at once a Preſent of his whole Heart, he might by the by have taken an account of her from <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> whom he ſaw perfectly knew her; He could not tell what Tricks ſhe might play with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38018:35"/>the <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> nor whether ſhe might Run with the Heart of a poor Squire, but he ſhut his Eyes when he gave it her, and blindly believed the Greatneſs of her Generoſity and good Nature; and indeed his Deſign was Pleaſant and Comical, for he thought it better to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe his Friends with his good Fortune, than to fore-ſtall them with an account of it before it came. The next Night the two Gentlemen went to a great Ball in <hi>Maſquerade, Altophel</hi> had the ſame Dreſs he had before, and was in his Meen and Faſhion the unalterable Squire: He was eſpied by his Miſtreſs, who came up to him and told him, That now ſhe believed ſhe had ſufficiently Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him the Senſe ſhe had of his good Qualities, by entertaining ſo much Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, which was a thing much contrary to her Temper, and her particular Intereſts in the Town, and that now ſhe expected that Generoſity from him, as at the ſame time to keep her Secrets, and alſo to forget that he had ever any knowledge of ſuch a Perſon. She went away without ſaying more, and <hi>Altophel</hi> followed her with a Heart Inflamed by this Indifference, and told
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38018:36"/>her a Thouſand things that might mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her to ſome Compaſſion, but ſhe under<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtood her ſelf too well to ſhew any Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morſe at all he could ſay, and whilſt ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mingled her ſelf with other Company the diſtracted Lover followed her, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a deſpair that was ready to make hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Breathe his ſoul at the Foot of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreſs: Every one that ſpoke to her, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>came a Rival, which <hi>Altophel</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed with all the Reſentments of Rage an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Madneſs; he Condemned every thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that was ſaid to her as Folly and No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſence, whilſt he allowed no man to ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well or gentilely that made Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her, and in particular one Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> very confident and very fine came up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her, and poured into her Ears and Addre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> made up of the Hoch poch, of <hi>Fren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but ſo ſtrongly put together and ſo much bad Sence, that <hi>Attoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> became juſtly Scandalized at it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a little to eaſe himſelf by Railing again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Rival, he went to find out <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to tell him what the Gentleman had ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken; he found him at laſt, and he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municated to him the Gentlemans who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſcourſe, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> told him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had an ill Judgement, to think that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:38018:36"/>Gallant who ſpoke thoſe things had not delivered himſelf very Handſomely and Gentilely, for thoſe words ſaid he are New, and <hi>French;</hi> and though in their Conjunction with ours they may not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Beautiful to you, yet here, where all things are Govern'd by Eſtimation and a Mode, we eſteem that a happy Genius which on all occaſions clings faſt to the Modiſh word, what ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of Damn'd Sence and Good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and till you Learn to ſpeak ſuch words Hardily and Gracefully, you will never move our Ladies to any great Compaſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> was much troubled at this Diſcourſe, firſt becauſe it excuſed a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, againſt whom the Squire believed he had ſuch juſt Accuſations, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it diſparaged thoſe Rules of Sence he had all his Life-time endeavoured to ſpeak by; but thus much we will ſay on the behalf of the poor Run-down Squire; that as it is certain amongſt thoſe Perſons who are the moſt Refined Wits of the Town, theſe words are ſo well mixt with our own, that the Symme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry makes up a very beautiful Eloquence, yet thoſe Gentlemen who are Barren in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38018:37"/>their Inventions, and that are not Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble of Suiting what is good of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> own with what is Modiſh of our Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours, many times come off with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Grace and an ill Compliment, and a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> valier of good Eſteem, underſtandi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>Violent</hi> was a word uſed on all O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſions in <hi>France,</hi> told a fine Lady th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe looked very Violently. This Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman, had he been happy in a go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Phancy, might better have uſed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> word in the Affairs of his own Paſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than to have blaſted ſo ſweet a Beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with it, if he had ſo great a deſire to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pear Intelligent in the graces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>French</hi> Tongue; but it is the unhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Thirſt of ſuch Perſons after Forre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Trifles, that has wearied our Preſs w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo many things of little Profit, and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lig'd the Vain-glorious part of that N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, to ſend us their Journals of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Concernments which are ſo no Mom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor Importance, ſuch as their <hi>Mercu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gallant,</hi> the <hi>Extravagance of Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cters,</hi> the <hi>Triflingneſs of Amours,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Half-witted Commendations of Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with an <hi>Arrogance</hi> which proclaims <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Obliged to Reverence all they do, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are Happy and Generous in themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:38018:37"/>they are a National Conſiderable to all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> for many admirable things, but they are ill Coppied in the Extravagant admiration which we ſhow of all their Actions. There are many things Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their Language, the Tranſlation of which has done us a great deal of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though it were to be wiſht that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe worthy Gentlemen who undertook <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, had pour'd the Subject more Clean and Unmixt out of one Language <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto another. There is no Notion nor Sence ſo conſiderable, but what may well be truſted with our own Words, and appear very Beautiful in them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her can they take it ill that any of their Theams and Conceptions where they Travel, ſhould appear in the Modes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Reſpective Countries when they come, which is the way to procure them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> General and kind Reception. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Imagine why we ſhould not deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be known by our own <hi>Genius,</hi> and our own <hi>Characters;</hi> I am ſure they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt Natural to us, and that Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age will ſupply the Defect of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iry and <hi>Volatile</hi> Graces that are pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar to other People: We do ill to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavour a Reſemblance with them in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38018:38"/>more Airy part of our Souls, whilſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> gravity which is Inſeparable from us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that appears very Handſome in us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not comply with that forced <hi>Lightneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> this is not ſpoken to Extol any thing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is our own, above the Excellencies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Neighbours, but only to affirm that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> natural Faſhion and Endowment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much better made uſe of upon all O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions, than the Introducing of any up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our Practice, in which our Affecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to it appear greater than our Dexte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the ill Humour of <hi>Altophel,</hi> by E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolling the Courtſhips of his Rival, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> went away, to Participate again of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> unpleaſing Entertainment, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more Violence to Condemn that for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſake of his own Averſion, which he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have no Aſſiſtance in from the Cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of others. The Lady had ſo good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Eye upon him, as to know when he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> near her, and ſhe did all things with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> admirable Grace, that made the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Squire ready to Die with Deſpair; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Danced ſo Incomparable, and receive addreſſes in ſo Charming a Faſhion, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every Beauty came through the reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her Admirers to the very bottom of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tophels</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:38018:38"/>Soul. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved whether he went, and though he knew not that Perſon whom he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet he imagined it to be her which he had ſeen at the Play; he went up to her, and told her that he had ſomething to Repreſent to her, worthy of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; which was the Condition of a young Gentleman, who appeared ſo much in Love with her that he purſued her into all places, as if the utmoſt which he Coveted was only to Breathe out his Soul at her Feet. She told him that ſhe came thither with a Dreſs above her Quality, and that ſhe was too mean to pretend to any thing of that Nature with a Gentleman: By this Reply, <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> was ſatisfied that he had found the right Perſon, and therefore ſaid to her, That he knew very well to whom he was Talking, and that it was with my Lady <hi>L.</hi> that he held his Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he named her ſo, that ſhe might believe he had miſtaken her, that ſo his Knowledge might be no Impediment to the Obſervation he deſired to make of her Actions, and he ſhun'd <hi>Altophel</hi> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Night, that ſhe might not ſee them together. The Squire for his part could
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38018:39"/>not refrain from wandering after her it to all the places whether ſhe went; ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> turn'd back once upon him, and ſaid t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, what is it that you would ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me? Diſcharge all your Sentiments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one time, I am unwilling to looſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Reſpect, which I have for a man tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> has a Secret of mine in his keeping, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſe good Qualities I approve of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much as is allowed amongſt thoſe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are Indifferent to all things; Have you an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing wherewith to accuſe a Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Humour? <hi>Altophel</hi> told her that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be the moſt miſerable Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the World, if ſhe put an end to ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a Friendſhip as ſhe had favoure him with, and that he had found thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſweeteſt Moments of all his Life in which he had Tranſported his So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the thoughts of her Eſteem; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it poſſible for him to Live an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> longer than he poſſeſſed that Felicity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lady, who underſtood all things which belong'd to a Charming Perſon told him that ſhe had much Exceede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Diſcretion of her Sex? when ſhe firſt Entertained a Converſation with o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe did not know, and that ſuch a Reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would ſufficiently Excuſe her for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38018:39"/>Inſenſible to all things ſhe heard from the moſt Vertuous and beſt Qualified Man in the World: <hi>Altophel</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for a Reply, which ſhe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring at that time to hear, prevented him, by ſaying, Why ſhould we Talk any more? We have proceeded far enough in an Acquaintance that had ſo ſtrange a Beginning, and I hope you will have no Reaſon to accuſe me of any thing, when I aſſure you that it ſhall end in this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ſo ſhe went from him, and preſently after out of the Room with her Company.</p>
            <p>When ſhe was gone, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> came to the Planet-ſtruck Squire, and asked him where he had been all that while? He replied, that he was obſerving of thoſe things which he had never ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>Altophel</hi> went Home poſſeſſed with different apprehenſions; he was Satisfied, in the firſt place, that the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy intended him no Artifice, by her cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him, and yet that which ſatisfied him that ſhe was Sincere, aſſured him alſo at the ſame time that he was never to receive any more Kindneſs from her. The poor Squire was unexperienced in thoſe admirable ways which are made
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38018:40"/>uſe of to inflame a Heart they intend for a Sacrifice, and <hi>Altophel</hi> was juſtly Puniſhed with ſo profound an Artifice who had neglected the Innocence and Integrity of <hi>Aſtraea;</hi> yet ſome minds are of that unhappy Temper, that they muſt be Treated with an abundance of Diſſimulation, to raiſe at once their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and to ſecure it, whilſt a plain ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity neither Inhaunces their Eſteem, nor preſerves them from Capriciouſneſs, which Defect of a good Underſtanding, has poſſibly given being to thoſe admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arts which are now ſo generally Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, by a Sex whoſe Tranquil and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Tempers, ſeem to have Faſhioned them to a juſt abhorrance of Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they now find a neceſſary Preſervative againſt Change and Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of their Lovers. And we will have that Charity for them, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they would willingly forget the Practice of it, if we would but once Learn to be Satisfied with a plain Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: It is certain, we can have no more than the Heart of thoſe we Love, which is not given with leſs Freedom and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence, becauſe it is preſented us with little Imbelliſhment and Ceremony. To
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38018:40"/>be intirely Beloved, is ſo incomparable a Bleſſing, that thoſe Capricious Fools who rate it by the hollow Careſſes and the ſtudied Charm, have yet nothing in their own Minds capable to conceive the Greatneſs of it, the moſt Courtly proteſtations and the Softeſt Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, make not ſo ſweet a Muſick as the Unartful Pantings of a faithful Heart; and which, being Tuned in a Reciprocal kindneſs, make up the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Harmony of Love.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:38018:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Intrigue of a great Lady about the Town.</head>
            <p>THat Lady whom <hi>Altophel</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, poſſeſſed all the parts of the moſt Refin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Diſſimulation, which ſhe uſed towards her Lovers without any Remorſe, or any Sence of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that ought to be Inſeparable from her Sex. It is difficult to Imagine what is the Pleaſure of procuring that Kindneſs from another, by a Thouſand Sleights, for which yet at the laſt we can only Return a counterſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Value. That Lover in whom we cannot meet with thoſe agreeble Endowments, as to be worthy of our moſt faithful Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, why ſhould we not let them alone, to find out a Heart that may delight in the Society of theirs? We commit a Robery in Nature, and take that to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38018:41"/>it to our Arts, which by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Impreſion is proclaimed to belong to another. That is the Heart on which we ſhould ſeize, in whoſe Inclinations we find all things that are ſuitable to our own: Nature has created a Parity of Minds, and though they come into the World at different times, yet they are made the Twins of one Inclination; as <hi>Nymphs</hi> have been aſſigned to <hi>Bowers,</hi> and as inſeparable Shadows purſue a Humane ſhape. A conſiderable part of the Worlds Felicity, is perverted by thoſe unjuſt Arts which are the Piracies of Beauty, and againſt which there ought to be granted by Love, Letters of Repriſal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> (who knew how much <hi>Altophel</hi> might fool himſelf in this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, becauſe he went ſo Seriouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, whilſt ſhe whom he Courted was a Lady of ſuch admirable Arts) was reſolved to mix it with ſome Comical Adventures; he in the firſt place Wrote a Letter which he cauſed to be conveighed to <hi>Altophel,</hi> which was in theſe Terms.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:38018:42"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A LETTER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Should never have done any thing of this Nature to a Stranger, were it not for that Value which I have for a Real Kindneſs. I am willing to believe I receive that from you, in theſe Regards you follow me with, and I am as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful for any thing that I could Requite without a Prejudice to that Juſtice which I owe to my Self and the Diſcertion of our Sex; however, the end for which I do it, ſhall for once Excuſe to my own Mind the freedom I Deſign, in telling you that to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row I ſhall be in the Park, at Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Clock in the Morning, and without any Company.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter was given to <hi>Altophel</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> who after he had Read it, demanded of him whence
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38018:42"/>it came; but as <hi>Altophel</hi> could not tell, becauſe of the Contents, ſo his Surprize had made him Uncapable of giving a Handſome account of it: Well ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> I ſee you have an Intrigue with ſome Lady, who is ſo Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that you will not Beatifie your Friend with the Knowledge of your good Fortune, and I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelf with wiſhing you all the Felicity and Contentment in it; the next Morning they both Roſe very Early, and <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> when he was ready, demanded of <hi>Altophel</hi> how he would ſpend the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: he told him that he had ſome Buſineſs to go abroad. Well, replied <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> I believe we are both a going up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one Deſign: Mine, I'le aſſure you, is an appointment, and I believe yours to be the ſame, and I wiſh that you may be as well Satisfied in yours, as I expect to be in mine: When he had ſaid theſe words, he gave him the Good-morrow, and went out. When <hi>Altophel</hi> found himſelf alone, he beat his Brains with thinking from whom that Letter ſhould come, which was given him the night before, and whoſe Directions he was juſt a going to follow. He could not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38018:43"/>readily Imagine who ſhould Write ſuch things to him as he had found in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he knew it was not at all agreeable to that Diſcourſe which had but two Nights before paſſed betwixt him and his cruel Miſtreſs, neither was it of the ſame force with their former acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and he muſt either Imagine that ſome ſeaſonable Kindneſs had Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely come in, to Obliterate the cruel Characters of a Paſſion which was grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſupportable to him, or that his Miſtreſs by beginning a new, ſhewed a diſlike of her former Treatment of him: There was a third account which the Youth might have given of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, and that was, That it was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by ſome Perſon to Mock him, and to Divert themſelves with his ſmall Experience. But <hi>Altophel</hi> had too much Self-love and Flattery about him, to Interpret any thing to the Prejudice of his good Qualities. And it is uſual with every one of us to believe all things by our Inclinations, and not our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whilſt a ſtrong Phancy carries Maſqued through all the Searches of the Mind, thoſe Objects which prove the Darlings of our Appetite, whence comes
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38018:43"/>the ill Succeſs of thoſe Admonitions which are given us by our Friends in contrary Actions, and on which we paſs ſuch untoward Interpretations of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Charity of their Souls, inſomuch that were it not for the Diſcharge of that Vertue and Affection, whoſe Buſineſs it is conſtantly to be Suggeſting of the Kindeſt things to thoſe we Love, no one would Intereſs themſelves in the Affairs of another Perſon, to which their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite and Inclinations prove an invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſcendant. Of thoſe two Accounts which <hi>Altophel</hi> gave to himſelf of this Adventure, we may Imagine he was more ready to conſider the latter; and that Soul which had been ſo ſweetly Charmed by his Miſtreſs, was willing to tread the moſt extravagant Mazes for the Love of her; where there is an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Paſſion, a little thing <hi>Cajoles</hi> and Allures it, and a Soul melted down by amiable Qualities, like flowing Mettles is turn'd any way, by the moſt eaſie Action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> when he had put theſe thoughts into his Head, permitted them to carry with a great deal of haſte to the place of that Appointment; when
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38018:44"/>he came there, he found but little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and going up the <hi>Mall:</hi> he ſaw a Lady and a Gallant walking together, to whom the Gentleman uſed a great deal of Ceremony; he conſidered her by all the Marks which he knew of his Miſtreſs, and found that her Height, her Dreſs, and her Gate, agreed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly with hers he came to find, (for all thoſe things had been thought of by <hi>Rhoderick</hi> in the Perſon he choſe) he followed them up both with Jealouſie and Rage; one time accuſing her of Folly and Diſſimulation, and at another, breathing Revenge upon that Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Perſon that had prevented his Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; he often look'd about to ſee if there was any other, and very willingly he would have found his miſtake in thinking it was ſhe whom he ſought, but he could find no Object ſo kind to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, and he was forced to follow this cruel Couple to the end of the <hi>Mall;</hi> when, to his greateſt amazement, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> turn'd ſhort upon him; the Lady was Maſqued, but ſhe feigned a little Diſorder at the ſight of <hi>Altophel,</hi> as <hi>Rhoderick</hi> alſo did himſelf, and made the Squire a ſign to purſue his Walk:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38018:44"/>That action made <hi>Altophel</hi> ſtark mad, to find a Rival, to find him in <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and to find him more beloved by the Lady he came to meet, ſhe looked after him, as <hi>Altophel</hi> alſo did after her, but <hi>Rhoderick</hi> appeared to have no ſuch Leiſure from a moſt amorous Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Here the Squire was wholly at a Loſs; for, to follow his Friend had been firſt Unkind, and ſecondly Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to Dog the Intrigue of another; and on the other hand, he thought that if <hi>Rhoderick</hi> only happened upon the Lady by accident, when ſhe had put him off ſhe had more agreeable Buſineſs with himſelf; ſo that Friendſhip, Love, and Honour, placed him like a <hi>Statue,</hi> whilſt they run a <hi>Tilt</hi> at each other in his Breaſt; at laſt Love (which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the moſt powerful in Youth) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him ſo far, that he went to ſhelter himſelf behind a Tree, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to wait the end of the Buſineſs; they walked up again, and after them came a very fine Lady, extreamly like her whom the Squire was in Love with, and her it was indeed, though ſhe was Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued, yet a thouſand Circumſtances made <hi>Altophel</hi> willing to believe it was her,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38018:45"/>when ſhe came to the end of the <hi>Mall,</hi> and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was gone back, ſhe pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led off her Maſque and looked about her: <hi>Altophel</hi> had a ſhort ſight of that charming Face, though her hood ſo much ſhaded it that he could not ſee it very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; when ſhe saw not what ſhe looked after, ſhe turned back in the <hi>Mall,</hi> but her poor <hi>Altophel</hi> was ready to breath his laſt at the foot of an Oak, through Rage and Vexation; firſt in thinking that if that was his Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miſtreſs, ſhe would believe that he had ſlighted ſo Charming a Kindneſs by not meeting her there; and then, if it ſhould not be ſhe, he would give a juſt cauſe of Diſpleaſure to that Lady who was walking with <hi>Rhoderick.</hi> Theſe Perplexities made him Groan moſt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically, whilſt <hi>Rhodericks</hi> Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was augmented by the thoughts of it, he phancied the Lady that came laſt was her indeed whom <hi>Altophel</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, and he knew the Squire was not far off, ſo that he knew in this Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth his Friend muſt be admirably Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed; he was ſure to keep near the laſt Commer, that <hi>Alltophel</hi> ſhould have no opportunity to come to her for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38018:45"/>any Information, without being taken Notice of by him, which he knew the baſhful Squire would carefully avoid; he was indeed Intangled in ſo many thoughts, as if he had been Fetter'd to the Tree, which protected him from the fight of all, and he became ſo Stupified with his Diſtraction, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to raiſe his Invention to the finding out of one poor Contrivance, whereby to Explicate himſelf. They came up again, and when they turn'd, ſhe that was alone went out of the Park, and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> after her, with the other Lady. <hi>Altophel</hi> expected their Return with a great deal of Impatience, but no <hi>Rhoderick</hi> nor Ladies appeared, which obliged the Squire to venture from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Tree to look for them in the <hi>Mall,</hi> he miſſed them there, which made him purſue them with a Speed as if he had been Hunting of Raviſhers; he knew not which way to go, and he would willingly have ſent one half of himſelf to this Gate, and the other to that, at laſt he fled to the Guards, but he could ſee nothing, and ſo went full of Vexation to his Lodgings, where he was told by his Footman that there had
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38018:46"/>been one to ſpeak with him, and to give him a Letter, which he had carried back again becauſe he was not at Home. This more and more perplexed his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and he ſeemed to have ſo much amorous Buſineſs upon his Hands, that he knew not which way to turn himſelf. He began to be ſatisfied that both the Letters could not come from one Perſon, and he phancied at length, that as faſt as he purſued his beautiful Miſtreſs with an ardent Paſſion, he was followed as Impetuouſly by another; this was a very pretty Imagination, and gave a ſtrange Contentment to the Squire, and though his Deſign was not very Brave nor very Manly, yet becauſe it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſant we will put it down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Adventures: For <hi>Altophel</hi> Inhumanely contrived to give the ſame Treatment to the Lady who was in Love with him, as he received from her he Courted, and he thought that could not be an ill Uſage which was Copied from her own Sex; he reſolved that every Frown he received he would charge it on his own Brow, and ſhoot it at his other Miſtreſs, whilſt every Smile ſhould, after it was caſt in the Mould of his own
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38018:46"/>Muſcles, be lodg'd in the Soul of the amorous Mind; every Expreſſion of Love and Anger that was Darted at him from his unknown admirer, he reſolved to new Feather with his Breath, and ſo let flie again the ſinging Accent. But ſo bloody a purpoſe could never be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful, and accordingly it happened with the Squire, for that Letter which was brought him in the Morning, came from no other but his old Miſtreſs, who was of a Humour very contrary from finding any Buſineſs for the Compaſſion of a Country Squire, and whatever gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Buſineſs ſhe undertook, it was Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with a Heart harder than thoſe Rocks that break a Tempeſt. She had ſent to him, it is true, to let him know that ſhe would be in the Park, but it was other Deſigns than Love that put her upon making ſuch Appointments; yet as Obſtinate as ſhe was, I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhe was a little out of Humour at the miſcarriage of her Plot; and ſhe could not but think it ſomething Odd, firſt to have her Summons diſobeyed by <hi>Altophel,</hi> and at that time to be Affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſight of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> whom ſhe knew to be his Friend; and ſhe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38018:47"/>might poſſibly have a little Remorſe, for contriving thoſe Deſigns upon a Youth whom Fortune appeared to Reſcue from her Arts. But when ſhe came Home and found that her Letter was not Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, ſhe took new Courage in her former Deſigns; ſhe reſolved to be that Afternoon at the Play, and after ſhe had let <hi>Altophel</hi> know that ſhe ſaw him there, ſhe turn'd her Head away, and looked no more upon him that Afternoon; which both Inflamed and Enraged him at once, and he was extreamly angry with himſelf, becauſe he knew that one way or other he had Diſobliged her by the Miſcarriages of the Morning; as ſhe was going out, <hi>Altophel</hi> got up to her and beg'd her to think of a time when ſhe would put an end to that Cruel uſage of him; to which ſhe coldly Replied, That it ſeemed he had other Buſineſs than to expect it from her, and ſo went into the Coach. This was a Theame large enough for the Squire to Declaim upon till he ſaw her next, but his Thoughts were ſo Confuſed and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, that it was Impoſſible for him to come to any Reſolutions; he knew not whether it were beſt for him to own
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38018:47"/>the Receipt of a Letter, becauſe he knew not whether it was hers; and if he ſhould ſay he had none, in that he phancied he might accuſe himſelf of a very great rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. When he came Home, <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> fill'd his Head with new Perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for he told him that he was Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized to meet him in the Morning, and asked him whether he was going, he ſaid that he only walked to take the Air: No; ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> you went to meet a young Lady that ſent you the Letter; but <hi>Altophel</hi> continued he, looking In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, had you not been both in Love and in haſte, I might have ſhewed you a Lady whom I am ſure you think very Handſome; I was walking with her where you met me, but you being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for warmer Amours, I thought could not then Digeſt ſo cold an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, as you muſt have had from her. <hi>Altophel</hi> grew Inflamed at this Diſcourſe, and knew not what Reply to make <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> only his Jealouſie obliged him to ſay, I was a going to meet no Woman, but though I was alone I did not want ſo unkind a Divertiſment as to have Interrupted my Friend when he was making Love; however though
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38018:48"/>the Lady appear'd to be very Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, yet I cannot believe it was any whom I admire; for you <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Perſon ſomething Scandalous, I phancy a civil Woman would not, for many good Conſiderations, put her ſelf into your Company. It is very well, my dear Squire, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that you think me not worthy the Favours of a fine Lady; however, what I had then were ſo very Indifferent, that you might have enjoyed them if you had pleaſed: I would not do a Lady of her Quality whom I had with me that wrong, as to procure her an ill Fame by my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that I tell to <hi>Altophel,</hi> is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to a Perſon whom I know Loves that Lady too well, to publiſh any thing to her Diſadvantage. My reſpect (ſaid <hi>Altophel</hi>) for the whole Sex is ſo great, that I would not do the leaſt Injuſtice to any one of them, and as I deprive them of nothing which they ought not to looſe, ſo I have always the Charity to believe that the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind preſerve the ſame <hi>Reverence</hi> for them. This is a Diſcourſe ſo Grave, replied<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Rhoderick</hi> with a Smile, That if I ſhould longer continue it, I might
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38018:48"/>chance to Dream of thoſe things that are contrary to my Humour, and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of more pleaſant Encounters which I have had to day, though I do not ſay they were with the Lady who has Obliged us to all this Seriousneſs, The faſhion with which <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ſpoke theſe things, and the words themſelves toucht <hi>Altophel</hi> to the quick, ſince he knew not what to gather from them, nor were they deſign'd for any other end, than equally to Ballance his Good and Ill Opinion. <hi>Altophel</hi> fell again to think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Adventures, he knew that it muſt be his Incomparable Miſtreſs, of whom <hi>Rhoderick</hi> diſcourſed, and ſo by Infallible conſequence it muſt be ſhe which was walking with him in the Morning, and alſo by the ſame irrefragable Argument, he concluded that there were things of that Nature betwixt her and <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> as were enough to Diſtract him with Jealouſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Altophel</hi> was now in a fair way to tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Rebel, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Perfections <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Sovereignty of his Miſtreſs; this is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e firſt Occaſion he has given us to take Notice of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable Niceneſs, than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more Impertinent in the Town; for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38018:49"/>he that makes Love there to a Lady ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Accompliſh'd, muſt be ſure to do it in the Croud of a thouſand Pretenders, nor will he ever be able to find that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at ſo much Leiſure, as to humour his Capriciouſneſs; and it is a Cuſtome with them, no longer to entertain a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, than he is good Natured, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with any Treatment they think to give him, for if it ſhould be otherwiſe Beauty would be forced to ſhrink from that Sovereignty it holds over our hearts, to a miſerable Lenitude to the Humours of its Admirers; and this is a very good Reaſon why there is no more ſerious Love amongſt them, becauſe the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing and Barterring of Hearts would be the Degrading of the Female Power, and give Beauty no Prerogative above Deformity; but to make us Love in ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght of our Teeth, and contrary to all thoſe Reſentments wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch an ill Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Inſpire us wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, is a Priviledge which raiſes and ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rts their Pride and Ambition. But <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ophel</hi> was not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of theſe thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs, and therefore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be Dogged with his Miſtreſs, for the Favours ſhe ſhewed to <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick.</hi> Poor Squire! Thou art ill Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38018:49"/>in that Place, where the firſt point of Wiſdom is not to Love at all, and the next never to admit of a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement after a juſt Quarrel; where thou waſt Born, it is found an agreeable Buſineſs to ſtudy pretty ways of Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, after an Innocent Anger, and after that to permit our Friendſhips to fall to pieces again only for the Pleaſures of a Reparation: There the Blood is ſweet, and the Days are long enough for ſuch Divertiſments, but in theſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, where reſides a perpetual Diſtruſt and ill Nature, the firſt Anger fires that Reſentment which neither thy Tears nor thy Blood could ever quench; they will admit of Reconcilements, but it is but the more to Gratifie their Revenge, by uſing a Diſſimulation with thoſe who have Diſobliged them: But it was in this <hi>Altophels</hi> good Fortune, that he could not Execute what he had Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, for his Miſtreſs appeared ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable at the next ſight he had of her, that he Sneaked ſufficiently in thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous looks he gave her, and ſhe not knowing thoſe unworthy Reſolutions he had taken, treated him with ſome ſort of Sweetneſs. She was a Lady that had
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38018:50"/>perfectly the Command of every Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and uſed them not according to her phancy, but thoſe Deſigns ſhe had upon any one.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:38018:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Duelling upon Love Account.</head>
            <p>THe place where <hi>Altophel</hi> ſaw her at this time, was the Park, where there was a great deal of Company walking, there was with the Lady only one Woman more and a Gentleman, the Illuſtrious <hi>Heroin</hi> drew <hi>Altophel</hi> after her along the <hi>Mall,</hi> and often Gratified him with a kind Look for that Obſervance. The Gallant that was walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with her, could not but take Notice of it, and as he thought the Squire a little Impertinent to follow them up and down, ſo he grew out of Humour with the Lady for Looking ſo often back upon him, and expreſſed ſo much to <hi>Altophel</hi> by his big looks, but the Squire who was not naturally very fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and particularly now, heated with good Fortune in his Love, was not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38018:51"/>to be Frighted from a place where he received ſo many Pleaſures, and <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> not only continued to do the ſame things whilſt he was in the Park, but alſo followed the Lady to the Coach. The Gallant, after he had put her in, came briskly up to <hi>Altophel,</hi> and asked him, What had Obliged him to follow that Lady? And demanded of him, what Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs he had with her? <hi>Altophel</hi> repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That he followed thoſe Inclinations in it, which he was not bound to give him an account of: The Gallant told Him that he had Affronted him in it, and that he expected Satisfaction from him, or he would get him Kick'd. <hi>Altophel</hi> anſwered him, that he would not force him to take ſuch a contrary Courſe, and with that acquainted him with his Name and Lodgings: Upon which the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Retired, and the next Morning ſent <hi>Altophel</hi> a Challenge, to meet him with his Second. The Squire accepted of it, but he was a little troubled to draw another Perſon into any Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies upon his account: Whilſt in ſuch Thoughts, he followed the Dictates of that Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tice and good Nature, which Cuſtome has Diſcredited in the Town:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38018:51"/>And indeed it is Cuſtome which does many ſtrange things, making the Od<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt actions to be well Interpreted, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would neither appear very Kind, nor very Generous to Involve an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Perſon in thoſe Actions which our own Folly or ill Nature pull upon us; certainly, every man ought by himſelf to ſupport thoſe Inconveniencies which he cauſes to himſelf, but a Fantaſtick Honour obliges me to run all the Riſques of the moſt Hot-headed and Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Perſons, and my good Nature and Civility, are Endowments which I can reap no benefit from, whilſt I muſt eſpouſe anothers Animoſity; that Blood which I endeavour to keep Calm. and Undiſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in my own Veins, cannot carry my Soul to the Periods of a long Life, whilſt I am not ſecure from having it thus Wrackt on the Tempeſts of a Strangers Rage: Neither am I leſs Precipitated by thoſe Extravagant Rules of Honour, upon the Ruin of my moſt dear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments; it is twenty to one but I may meet againſt me in the Field, that Perſon whom I eſteem above all the reſt of Mankind, and I may either Kill him; Whom to Wound proves my own
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38018:52"/>Murder, or Die by that hand which had Signed an Eternal Friendſhip with me. Certainly, never any Tyrannick Cuſtom was ſet up in the World, ſo Barbarous and Extravagant as this of Duels, and it muſt have been in Hell, that the black Shapes of that Honour were firſt drawn, which would appear to us things of the greateſt Horror were they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to by any other <hi>Votaries,</hi> than the blinded Rage and Fury of our Souls; but Love, Youth, and Cuſtome, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated <hi>Altophel</hi> upon an action that was ſo contrary to him, and he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſpoke to <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to be his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which he readily conſented to: They went in the Morning, and they had juſt began to Fight, when there came into the Field a very fine Lady, and putting her ſelf betwixt them, ſhe Obliged them to give over; when ſhe had pulled off her Maſque, ſhe was known to be <hi>Altophels</hi> Miſtreſs, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had ſpoken ſome angry words to <hi>Altophels</hi> Enemy, ſhe Obliged him to wait upon her away, whilſt his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond accompanied him in the ſame Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, the other Two went Home-another way; as they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38018:52"/>along, <hi>Altophel</hi> could not but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the great Juſtice and Generoſity of the Lady, to prevent the ſhedding of any Blood upon her account. In that, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> ſhe has appeared more Compaſſionate than many Ladies of the Town, who make a Divertiſment of thoſe Quarrels they procure; and with an Indifference, like theirs who beheld the <hi>Roman Gladiators,</hi> they make but a Sport of the looſing Lives even in them for whom they avow a Kindneſs. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> thoſe Rules of Love ought not to be approved of by the Lover, and nothing ſhould paſs for Eſteem from a Miſtreſs, which does not agree with that we have for our ſelves In our ſelves, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> we value our Honour above our Lives, and thoſe that love us, ſhould have the ſame care of our good Qualities which we have our ſelves: I ſhould readily excuſe them from that care of my good Qualities, replied the Squire, and I ſhould not Fancy to be faſhioned by any ones Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour but my own. In that your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> is contrary to mine, ſince I ſhould never value any thing about me, if it had not an equal
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38018:53"/>eſteem of the Ladies. Well, ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> but as to the preſent Adventure; I think the Lady was much more Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to put an end to our Quarrel, than to have ſuffered us to Kill each other, only to eſteem the Gallantry of the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Liver. You having, ſaid <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> a particular eſteem for this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, will ſet your ſelf to Juſtifie and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire all ſhe does, and ſo you are not a fit Perſon to be Diſcourſed with at this time: This was all the Notice <hi>Rhoderick</hi> took of the Quarrel, which he would not further enquire into, becauſe he found <hi>Altophel</hi> not very forward to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Reaſons of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:38018:53"/>
            <head>SECT. VII. <hi>About Arreſts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS they were going Home, there came a Select Number of Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, and caught hold of <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> taking his Sword preſently from him; <hi>Altophel</hi> thought at the firſt, that it had been ſome Perſons came to ſeize them upon account of the Duel, but his Friend quickly acquainted him that it was an Arreſt, which Obliged the Squire to draw his Sword, though he knew not what to do with it In that Company; this was to <hi>Rhoderick</hi> the worſt Encounter of the Two, and he was ſo much a Man of the Town
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38018:54"/>Humour, that he was more willing to run all the hazards of a Duel, than to fall into thoſe Troubleſome inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of owing Money: but their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners were ſo Nimble, that they preſently run him to a Tavern, whither <hi>Altophel</hi> followed him to be his Second, in an Engagement of a different Nature to the other. The Warrant was for Two Hundred Pounds, which was a Debt contracted by one of <hi>Rhoderick</hi>'s Miſtreſſes, with a Tradeſman, and which the Gallant had paſſed his word for; it ſtood in the Citizens Book very peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, whilſt <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and his Miſtreſs held a Friendſhip; but when he left her, the ſpightful Lady amongſt the other ways of her Revenge, had in particular Obliged the Tradeſman to deal thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly with <hi>Rhoderick;</hi> he Swore as deeply againſt her for the unworthineſs of the action, as he had formerly done to her for the putting himſelf into her Favour; but theſe laſt Imprecations were to the ſame purpoſe as the former, ſerving only to Agitate that Wind which carried them far enough from the Soul to which they were Directed: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, had they been Managed with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38018:54"/>the greateſt Force and Judgment, it would have been impoſſible for them to have made any Impreſſions in a heart ſo hard, as is carried in the Boſomes of the Town. After <hi>Rhodericks</hi> Rage was a little abated, he thought of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Remedy to ſuch Diſaſters, which was to give Bail to the Action, and <hi>Altophel</hi> was the Perſon, neither could he refuſe it to his Friend, and to a man who had that morning done him a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a more dangerous Nature; it was as readily accepted of by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who were glad of ſuch good Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as <hi>Altophel,</hi> whoſe Fortune was freſh and Unblaſted. When this was done, the two Friends went Home, where a little after, <hi>Altophel</hi> had this following Letter brought him.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:38018:55"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A LETTER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Hope you will now be Satisfied with that Compliance I have deſired from you, and Expect no more Familiarity with me; I have Received new Motives to Settle that Reſolution in my Mind from the Adventure of this Morning, and ever to Speak to a Man who has in that manner been Engaged upon my Account, is an Inconvenience I muſt Reſolve to ſhun, though I ſhall ſo far Conſider my former Good-will to you, as to wiſh you Well, and particularly that you may be more Happy than you could ever have been in that Kindneſs, which you deſired from me.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> read this Letter with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Diſtraction of mind, but there are
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38018:55"/>ever two ways by which we adminiſter a Conſolation to our ſelves upon ſuch Occaſions. The firſt is, To put a low Value upon that Eſteem we looſe, and to believe it is no Infelicity to us: And the other is, by a ſtrange Flattery which we afford to our ſelves, by which we Disbelieve any thing we deſire ſhould be untrue, and by a ſtrange Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentation particular to a Love-ſtruck mind: We give very pleaſant Reaſons of thoſe contrary Opinions which we are willing to Embrace. This latter was the Relief of <hi>Altophel,</hi> thoſe unkind things which were told him, were by his own Imagination interpreted as pieces of <hi>Decorum</hi> or Prudence, and not the Expreſſions of a Reſolution which was preſently a going to be Executed, for the Lady was juſt to what ſhe had told him; but what were the Motives ſhe made uſe of, to perſwade her ſelf to an action ſo much Contrary to her firſt Deſign, we cannot determine; whether ſhe believed that his perpetually Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting with <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> might ſome time or other, procure him the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe things that went about
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38018:56"/>the Town to her Prejudice; or whether ſhe being a Lady of a great Birth, of a high Spirit, and poſſeſſing many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Qualities, ſhe might at laſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to her ſelf the Illneſs of that Deſign ſhe had engaged her ſelf in, and feel a Remorſe to receive ſo unfeigned and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent a paſſion as ſhe believed <hi>Altophel</hi> had for her, only with Art and Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; we ought to believe it was the latter Conſideration that prevailed with her, ſince a Perſon of a generous Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, will one time or other Reſcue themſelves from thoſe ill Actions into which their Appetites or Inadvertency often Precipitate them; that Honour, which is the meaſure of all things in a Noble mind, though ſome miſchievous Accidents and Paſſions may often Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure it, yet it ſeldom fails to break out from the thickeſt Clouds with ſo much brightneſs, as to be capable to Direct the Owner in the Paths of ſome Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity. <hi>Altophels</hi> Miſtreſs got theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts on her ſelf, and ſhe Compleated them by withdrawing for the preſent from the Town: The Squire hunted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her in every Company, and he loved not himſelf in all thoſe Places where he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38018:56"/>had ſeen her, becauſe that beautiful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon appeared in none of them, whoſe only preſence kept them from ſeeming Deſolate to him; a Love that was ſo dear to the Squire, could not be ended without ſomething of a Tragical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and he grew ſo Melancholly, as to keep his Bed for many days. <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> that imagined how it was with him, ſeeing the Extremity he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, at laſt reſolved to Adminiſter what he believed would prove an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Remedy; and he accordingly one day came to him, and told him, That though he was unwilling to Concern himſelf in any of his particular Affairs, yet he thought it belong'd to his Juſtice, and was moreover an act of his Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſet him right in one thing, by which he ſtrangely wrong'd himſelf. I know, continued <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that you are in Love, and that you are in Love with the Lady who put an end to our Duel; but you love her, <hi>Altophel,</hi> without any knowledge of her and though I am not ſo Inhumane as to delight in Publiſhing any thing to the Diſadvantage of ſo fine a Lady; yet my Kindneſs to you, will Oblige me to make you a Relation, that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38018:57"/>will alone Cure your Paſſion, and reſtore you to your good Humour, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did. Thoſe things which <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> heard, much troubled and amazed him, but he would not appear ſo unkind to the Memory of a Perſon whom he had ſo paſſionately loved, as to permit them to Lodge a moment in his Soul; and he at once endeavoured to forget them, and the Lady who was unhappy in them, which was a good Endowment in the Squire ſince thoſe Objects that have received the Kindneſs and Careſſes of our Souls, when we find our ſelves Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to give them no longer that Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is but a common Juſtice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them thence with Civility and Reſpect, and not to keep them any longer there, only to Expoſe them to the Affronts of our Reſentment: Every thing that we have loved, does from that Paſſion receive a title to our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Difference, which conſiſts in forgetting thoſe Perſons whom we cannot remember with pleaſure. <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> being in this Condition, very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently applied himſelf to thoſe things that might Divert him from an ill Humour, which is a bad Quality ſo extreamly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38018:57"/>in the Town; one thing he thought of in very good time, and that was the ill Events of his Loves, and he very ſeaſonbly concluded, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good Succeſs others might find in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſerious Paſſion, it was not his Fortune <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o meet with the ſame, and therefore what Encounters he found of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he reſolved to make no very grave Buſineſs of them. And <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly told him one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beauty was the firſt thing that had Captivated him in the Town, but that he ſerved it in a wrong manner, ſince it was not a place that admitted of great and ſerious Paſſions, becauſe the Humour of it, was for the preſent only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccommodated to eaſie and gentle Loves. But <hi>Altophel,</hi> ſaid he, ſince you find your ſelf not Inclined to thoſe Soft and Good-natured Paſſions, which neither wound nor Kill; it were better for you, ſince your Temper is Heroick, to Aſſociate with ſome of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Wits, and take your Inſtructions from them: With theſe you muſt know, <hi>Altophel,</hi> every one is ambitious to Conſort himſelf, and amongſt them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are great and powerful Factions, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38018:58"/>already is commenced the <hi>Bellum Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> with all the appearances of a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Animoſity; thoſe things which are diſputed for, are the lofty <hi>Drama,</hi> and the amarous <hi>Stanza,</hi> the Buſineſs of theſe Contrary Factions is to Cut in pieces the Reputation of each other, and to Damn all their Productions for unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Stuff. I had rather, ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> obſerve a Neutrality in ſo hot a Quarrel, than to endanger either my Judgment or my Reputation, where I have no Intereſts that Oblige me to it. But that is not (replied <hi>Rhoderick</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Activity and Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the preſent Age, whoſe happy Genius enterprizes upon all things, and to eſteem nothing ſo dear as to Decline the Expoſing of it. If you will be a Wit, you muſt aſſociate with one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or the other, and I hope you will not be ſo unkind as to Deſert your Friend: For I am of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſide, and for your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement I muſt tell you, That it is the moſt proſperous, and has the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Party. If you have taken that ſide only for thoſe Conſiderations, replied <hi>Altophel,</hi> methinks you have done an Action contrary to your Honour, which
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38018:58"/>ſhould eſpouſe a Quarrel for the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of it, and not to follow Fame or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in a Diſpute ſo Important as that of Wit; the Juſteſt ſide may fall into Contempt, whilſt Vertue is not always meaſured by Succeſs. But ſince all men, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> have no more to do with Wit than to enjoy the Fame and the Reputation of it, it is better to aſſociate with a Celebrated party, than to be unſeaſonably Generous, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſupport a Damn'd <hi>Pretenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> he that puts in his Talent to the greateſt Maſs of Wit, like him that ventures in a rich Company, has thoſe Returns which are Conſiderable and Eaſie too; I can now paſs for a Wit, by keeping ſuch Company, by Rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome Verſes, and by Damning the contrary ſide. But I can never, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> allow of what you ſay to be the Gallantry of a true <hi>Cavalier,</hi> ſince it is more becoming a <hi>Heroe,</hi> and a great Wit ſuch as <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> to Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate a Sinking ſide, and to Raiſe for himſelf a Fame, by carrying Conqueſt and Victory to a Party that ſhould owe it to his Sufficiency alone. My dear Squire, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> waving the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:38018:59"/>Flattery of that Diſcourſe, I muſt tell you, that ſuch great Exploits were for Ages more Hardy and leſs Voluptuous; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Genius is compoſed of Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and Wit like our Modes is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed for its agreeableneſs, and ſitting eaſie about us. Therefore, ſaid <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> you ſhould the more endeavour to Reſcue ſo Illuſtrious an Endowment from the power of ſuch Men, who whilſt they pretend to pay it Veneration, hold it in Servility; Wit had ever greater Oblations and Sacrifices allowed it, and a more profound Homage there's done it now. Ah, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that was the Cauſe of its Tyranny and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Capriciouſneſs, but we have now made it more Gentle and Propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Mankind, by forcing it to a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, in more Eaſie and Careleſs addreſſes; he that formerly came a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to it, muſt bring a Train of <hi>Volumnes</hi> with the Oblation of ſome Signal and Uſeful undertaking; but now it is Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a Poem, or a Love-ſong, ſo increaſing the Number of <hi>Votaries</hi> whilſt it diſpences with the burthen of infinite Qualifications. By that way, replied <hi>Altophel,</hi> will come in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38018:59"/>Neglect of it, for when the Eſteem of Wit is eaſily Purchaſed, the Fame of it will be leſs Conſiderable; and the Pretences growing Common, none will undertake an extraordinary Service for what is enjoyed by eaſie Attempts. But why, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> ſhould any Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len precepts thruſt the greateſt part of Mankind out of ſo happy and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious a Reputation as that of Wit, which is now ſo amicably Shared indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently amongſt all the World? me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks nothing would be ſo happy as the <hi>Levelling</hi> of Underſtandings, and every thing that is above this peaceful Community, ſhould be Damned for a Tyrannick Non-ſence, which would quickly Diſcourage all the Pedantick Ambition after a Priority in Wit. This ſort of <hi>Levelling,</hi> replied <hi>Altophel,</hi> I am a great Enemy to, and I would have the Government of Wit to be <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crical.</hi> Ah <hi>Altophel,</hi> replied <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> if you knew the Sweetneſs of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought a VVit, and yet the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of procuring and preſerving that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle according to the Old <hi>Modes,</hi> you would more eaſily be of my Opinion, ſince it has been found in Times no more
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38018:60"/>Remote than our own: How uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Succeſs of the beſt VVits have been? And thoſe who have a long while received the moſt extravagant Elogies and <hi>Encomiums,</hi> have ſuddenly, and ſtrangely too, fallen into the Scandal of being Dull and Inſipid, and rather to Dote than to be VVitty in all their VVritings. Every thing, replied <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> has a time to Flouriſh, and to Fade, and thoſe Endowments which have the moſt Pleaſed and Obliged the VVorld, may meet with Inconſtancy and Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; but that does not Leſſen the real Eſteem of a truly glorious Quality. VVell, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> I ſee we cannot Convince one another, and ſo ſhould give over the Diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:38018:60"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> A Diſcourſe againſt Plays.</head>
            <p>AS they made an end; there came into their Lodgings two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were eſteemed two admirable VVits: <hi>Rhoderick</hi> after the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, told them that they came ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happily at that time, becauſe he had ſo great a deſire to preſent a young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to them, that wiſht nothing ſo much as to be admitted one of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, that he might faſhion his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by thoſe Habiliments and Modes, which they allowed of Senſe and Reputation; with that he preſented <hi>Altophel</hi> to them, who made them the beſt Complements he could upon this Occaſion, after which they all went out to Supper. <hi>Altophel</hi> ſet himſelf to catch at every thing which was ſpoken in this Company, and brought together all
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38018:61"/>his Senſe, that he might receive as he ought, thoſe Conceptions which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from men ſo Extraordinary: The firſt Subject they fell upon, was a Lady whom the Squire had before heard of, but they handled her in ſuch barbarous Language, and with ſo many Obſcene freedoms, that the Modeſt youth grew really Compaſſionate of the Injured Lady, and could not but fancy ſhe felt a certain Pain and Indignation at the Violences were done her in that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; he would have forgiven them, had they with any Modeſty taken from her a good Name, or with the leaſt ſhew of Regret mentioned her Infirmities, but he was juſtly Scandalized at the blunt Rudeneſs, with which they Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed her Honour and her moſt Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Concernments; he could not but Reflect upon the extream Civility to that Sex, which was found in the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous VVit of former Ages, whilſt it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them Knights Errant to defend their Honours, never ſcrupling to ſend them half the VVorld over in ſearch of a Raviſher; but now he found that Men of the greateſt pretences to VVit and admirable Endowments, not only Frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38018:61"/>ſtab their Honour, but drag them out of the moſt ſecret Receſſes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, whilſt they Inhumanely Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize and Butcher them in their Bloody diſcourſes; but the Tenderneſs and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility of <hi>Altophel</hi> was happily taken off of the Rock, by one of thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens having an occaſion to go out of the Coach about a little Buſineſs, in which he was accompanied by <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> whilſt <hi>Altophel</hi> was left alone to ſo great a Wit, and without the <hi>Medium</hi> of a Friend betwixt himſelf and a Perſon whom he could not conſider as he did the reſt of Mankind; the Gentleman asked him how long he had been in the Town, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had yet made Choice of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and Courted her with Songs: <hi>Altophel</hi> replied, that he was yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miſtreſs, but that when he ſhould, Chooſe her, he could not be ſo happy as to Court her in that Poetick Faſhion: you muſt then expect, anſwered the other, not to be very Fortunate in your Love, ſince that is the way of Courtſhip which the Ladies have now made Choice of; they have long enough looked in their Glaſſes to take an account of all their Beauties, and to behold them in the Contortion
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38018:62"/>and Grimaces of their Lovers, is a Mirrour for which they have now juſtly an Abhorrance. To conſider them in that Love we pretend to have for them, is a Repreſentation ſubject to ſo many Exceptions, that it is as juſtly Negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by this incredulous Age: It is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then in the Beautiful and lively Draughts of Poetry, that they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and admire themſelves. I ſhall ſurely, replied <hi>Altophel,</hi> make a very ill Lover, if all the ſincerity of my Heart will not ſupply the defect of my Poetry. This is a Town, ſaid the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, that pretends to Examine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Out-ſide and Appearance, whilſt a bountiful Expreſſion is received with as good an Eſteem, as all the Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes of an amorous Heart.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, continued he, ſince I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you have no Inclination for our <hi>Amours,</hi> How do you like our other Gallantries, and particularly our Plays? As for the Plays, replied <hi>Altophel,</hi> my Inclination for them is like that of others who comes Strangers to the Town, which is, to eſteem what we ſee before any thing we hear; beſides the great Difficulty that it is now made of Judging
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38018:62"/>that ſort of Wit, whilſt the Poets have amongſt themſelves rendred all Sence ſo Fantaſtical, that a man can hardly tell which is it amongſt thoſe Condemn'd things he hears. Wit ſeems to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved amongſt you, not for any of its Native beauties, but for the particular <hi>Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance</hi> which it wears, whilſt ſome men will admire the moſt trifling conceptions, under the Protection of one whom they applaud; and at the ſame time they make no ſcruple to Damn very gallant thoughts, if they are the Iſſue of a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Brain. Certainly, replied the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Eſteem muſt be the meaſure of the beſt Sence, and in ſo vaſt a Confuſion of contrary things, and in ſo much. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs as the World finds at preſent, it is neceſſary that the richeſt Notions ſhould be taken by Content; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the trouble of counting over their Value. I am of the Opinion, anſwered the Squire, that the Town at preſent drives too great a Trade of VVit, and has particularly too much Poetick Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon its hands: It happens, repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the other, in the Common-wealth of Poetry, as it does in other States; where the Allurement and Thirſt of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38018:63"/>multiplies the Aventurers, which is at laſt a Ruine of the Commerce it ſelf, and that Wit which has procured ſo many Advantages to the Owners of it, by falling into many hands will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grow very little Valued. It is Fame and Reputation which makes all VVit currant, and if it looſes that ſtamp it will manage no Intereſts in the World. It would be happy (replied <hi>Altophel</hi>) if that Fame could conſider more the good of Mankind, and chooſe thoſe <hi>Mettals</hi> to Impreſs upon, which have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Value equal to that of her <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</hi> But that Coyn, replied the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, would move more heavily in the World, and Men would not ſo ſoon grow rich in Reputation; the Treaſures of the preſent Wit (ſaid <hi>Altophel</hi>) are ſo quickly got together, that the Juſtice of procuring it is ever queſtioned; and many have Declined the Trade, becauſe of a juſt abhorrence which they have for the Scandal of it. I ſee (replied the other with a Smile) that you have brought out of your Country thoſe Scruples of mind which muſt be removed by a conſtant uſe of our Divertiſments, which I hope will give you alſo contrary Impreſſions.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:38018:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> The Cuckolding of Two Lawyers.</head>
            <p>AS he ended that Reply, they came to the place where they were to Sup, they had been there but a little while when <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and the other Gentleman came to them, and brought two very fine Ladies; they were ſtrangely Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant with them before Supper, and the Ladies came thither in ſo good a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, that they conſented to everything was deſired of them. <hi>Altophel</hi> though he coveted not the Knowledge, yet he was forceably Inſtructed in ſome things that he had till then been Ignorant of; as in particular, whether the Ladies Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were tied above, or below the Knee; and how many Buckles in the Garter went to the making of a Love-knot; what number of Petticoats it is neceſſary to wear about the Equinoctial;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38018:64"/>and above all, with how much Freedom a well-ſhaped VVoman will Expoſe her delicate Limbs to the ſight of all the VVorld; as if Modeſty in that Sex had at firſt been nothing elſe but the Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Deformity. A great many other things without doubt came that day to <hi>Altophels</hi> knowledge, but they were of that Value that he could never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to Divulge them. They had an excellent Supper, and ſo much Mirth as would have Digeſted the hardeſt Fare in the VVorld; as ſoon as that was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they went to Play, and at the ſame time Drank abundantly. <hi>Altophel</hi> in a little while Loſt all his Money, which conſiſted in a great many pieces of good Gold, and he Loſt with them the beſt part of his Senſe and Underſtanding; he exactly followed the Diſcipline of the Stoicks, who (that we might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Misfortunes) adviſe us to harden and deaden the Senſes; VVine had helpt <hi>Altophel</hi> more nimbly to that Quality, than Philoſophy could poſſibly have done. VVhen the Company had Tired themſelves with all Exploits, <hi>Altophel</hi> being the leaſt uſed to thoſe Endurings,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:38018:64"/>fell aſleep, whilſt the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany left him, and one of the Ladies very Inhumanly took his Breeches with her; he at laſt awaked, and ſtragled out of the Room into the Street, when he came there it was juſt Day-break, and the want of his Breeches made him a very Ridiculous ſpectacle to thoſe that were going along; at laſt he happened upon a Coach, into which he got and was drove Home to his Lodgings, where after he had Recovered his Senſes by a ſound ſleep; he awaked, and fell to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf about his laſt nights Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance; the want of his Gold, the diſorder of his Stomach, and the loſs of his Breeches put him quite out of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and he awaked <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to be guided out of theſe Perplexities; but he was plunged deeper in them, when his Friend told him that he had plaied away all his Gold, and that he had made Love like a true Cavalier; but, ſaid the Squire, did I play away my Breeches too? No, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> I did not ſee you without them, and I am ſorry that I was ſo unkind in my Drink, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the going Home with my Miſtreſs before the care which I ought to have
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38018:65"/>had of my Friend. However I will (ſaid he) make an Inquiry after your Clothes; but that trouble was ſaved, for as they were talking, there came one in with the Breeches and a Letter directed to <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> in which the Lady deſired him to ask <hi>Altophels</hi> pardon for taking away thoſe things which ſhe had now reſtored; ſhe confeſſed that ſhe had done it with little Judgment, and leſs Compaſſion, ſince they were his Defence in thoſe places where he was the weakeſt, and where he ought to be the beſt Fortified; but as for the Letters that were in the Pocket, ſhe had ſeized on them, and wiſhd ſhe might but know the writer, to admoniſh her to receive no more Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from a Lover of ſo cold a Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ſhewed the Squire the Letter, who was more troubled at the loſs of his Gold and his Letters, than at the blunt Character which the Lady beſtowed upon him; but he diſſembled all to <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> only asked him what Ladies thoſe were that had been ſo free with them the night before? They are, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> the VVives of two excellent Lawyers: That may be, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> for their Practices are as Unconſcionable
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38018:65"/>as their Husbands; and they are as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py too, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> ſmiling in a Vindictive Eloquence. I will (ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi>) allow them to be as good at Railing, but I beſeech you, How do theſe two great Cuckolds ſupport the Misfortune of having ſuch bad VVives? Oh, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> with the greateſt Tranquility in the VVorld, they are the moſt tender Husbands that Live, and Eſteem themſelves the moſt happy of all men in ſuch Fond and Careful VVives. It is very ſtrange, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> that none of theſe Extravagancies ſhould ever come to their Knowledge, one of which is great enough to make them Hang themſelves, without the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of that Remorſe which they ought to have for their bad Practices. And I wonder moreover, continued the Squire, why they affect the Company of ſuch great VVits as were with us the laſt Night. There is a very good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for that, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> becauſe the Converſation of the Law being Rough and Blunt, Obliges the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to have a Recourſe to the Soft and Gentle Society of the Poets. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, replied the Squire, the Society
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:38018:66"/>was Soft and Gentle enough, but I could eaſily Excuſe them from pretending to that greatneſs of VVit which they are ſo much admired for. You are ſo very Idle, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> as to eſteem all good Sence by thoſe damn'd Rules which you Learned at School, from your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Pedants; but here we value VVit by the Humour and the Softneſs of it. Nay, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> if that be the chief Ingredient in Wit, I Congratulate thoſe Gentlemen which were with us; for thoſe things I heard then, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Verſes which one of them Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, were very Flat and Dull. You muſt know ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that the Thoughts which now procure a good Liking, are ſuch which never attempt to break the Brain in being underſtood; the preſent Genius is more Civil, and better bred than to do any Violences to the Underſtanding. I wiſh (replied <hi>Altophel</hi>) the preſent Practices had ſo much Kindneſs in them; and for my part I had rather have loſt the Opinion of my good Sence, than the poſſeſſion of ſo much Gold. That is, ſaid <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> according to your narrow Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Reputation; for what is Money
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38018:66"/>to the moſt dear Concernments of Love and Wit; Oh! it is abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (ſaid <hi>Altophel</hi>) for the Attainment of both, ſince I never knew a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, that paſſed either for a great VVit, or an accompliſht Perſon. You Judge very Sordidly (ſaid <hi>Rhoderick</hi>) to meaſure all things by Money, and not by Vertue and excellent Qualities. Yes, ſaid <hi>Altophel</hi> Laughing, thoſe are things very finely eſteemed amongſt you, I ſhould have a very great value for Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and the good Endowments of the Mind, but <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> I have not met with them ſince I came to this place; and I therefore eſteem Money, becauſe it makes up all things of that Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which paſſes amongſt your ſelves. He that cannot make Love, that cannot Drink, and Play, and bear up to all the Modes of the Town, I am ſure is the moſt deſpicable VVretch that Lives; and all theſe things are fed by the happy Current of Money, and muſt be ſo, except you could according to the Project of <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> procure VVine, Garniture, and VVomen for the Stanzas of a Love-ſong. By your Rules of Judging (replied <hi>Rhoderick</hi>) a young
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38018:67"/>Squire ſuch as your ſelf, coming to this Town, would Rival all the moſt Famed and Experienced Gallants of it. Without doubt, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> their Humours are not ſo Obſtinate, but that he which had Money enough, might eaſily make a Purchaſe of all your Female Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities; they Love you not ſo well to be Fetter'd in your Gallantry and Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to the Prejudice of richer Flights. Prethee, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> do not Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize the Generoſity and Fidelity of our Women: do you believe that any thing except an infinite Kindneſs could Oblige them to Expoſe their Honours if they are ſingle, and their Reputation and Quiet if they are Married, for our ſakes? By the by I muſt tell you, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> that your Gratitude is wholly Extraordinary for ſuch Favours, ſince I believe you never Obtained thoſe things of any Woman, but you took as much Pleaſure to Talk of it, and to Divulge it, as you did in the Enjoyment it ſelf; and there is no Lady that has at any time done thoſe Injuries to her ſelf, but is the Table-talk of the Town. Oh! ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> we ſpeak of thoſe things only amongſt our ſelves, into which
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38018:67"/>Company there never comes an Uxori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fop, nor a well-wiſher to Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, ſuch as your Squire ſhip; But is not the Kindneſs of the Ladies extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, that can overlook ſuch great Infirmities out of the Love they bear us? All ſuch things, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> have a Motive from within the Perſon that does them, and you aſcribe that in vain to your Courtſhips and Gallantries, that is alone produced by a luſtful Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance; that fire is perpetually Burning in their Breaſts which you pretend to enkindle, and thoſe with whom you take ſo much pains to procure their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, would Ramp upon you if you ſhould neglect them. You very much Scandalize all Woman-kind, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> and that which we excuſe as their good Nature, and the effect of long and Cunning Importunities, you make to be a Prompt and Flaming In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. I only ſpeak of thoſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Altophel,</hi> that have hardened themſelves by the heat of their own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and not ſuch which ever carry about them the moſt tender Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Vertue and Juſtice; She that is thus fortified is Invincible to all aſſaults,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38018:68"/>whilſt that Perſon that is not, will be ſure one time or other to Miſcarry, though the moſt watchful Jealouſie pretends to Guard her, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Conſiderations of Prudence offer themſelves to be her Security. Then it ſeems, replied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> that you would truſt a Wife and a Miſtreſs in any Company, you now abound as much with good Nature, and are a young Gentleman that Merit extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Women. Yes, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> that is my Opinion, I would truſt her with a Thouſand Lovers, for if ſhe is Vertuous, ſhe will be Obſtinate to the utmoſt Attempts; and if ſhe is not, all Jealouſie and Precaution is in vain. You make me Mad with this Diſcourſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> ſince I tell thee I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came near a. VVoman that could withſtand me when I Courted her. That may be, ſaid <hi>Altophel,</hi> ſince none but thoſe that were willing to be Courted would ever have come near <hi>Rhoderick;</hi> you ſet upon the VVilling and the Amorous, and then Judge the whole Sex, for the ſake of thoſe that Hunt occaſions of Love with an Induſtry great as your own, which yet is not out of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38018:68"/>eſteem which they have for your good Qualities, but from the heat of their own Inclinations; therefore <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> be not ſo Uncharitable as to think there are not many glorious VVomen which ſeparate themſelves, with a juſt abhorrence, from thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies for which you Condemn the whole Sex. Though you have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met with any but thoſe who have been ill enclined, yet you ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there are Perſons infinitely better Qualified, in a Sex, which has other Beauties and Excellencies belonging to it, than you have yet comprehended. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> only Laughed, and made no Reply to the Squire, when there came into their Lodgings thoſe two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that had Supped with them the night before. Come, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick</hi> to them, your Company is very ſeaſonable, for this young Diſcourſing Squire will not yet receive thoſe good Principles which he ought to Faſhion himſelf by: VVe gave him a Taſte, ſaid one of them Smiling, the laſt night, of what belongs to true Gallantry and Generoſity, whilſt we united all our Pleaſures in one En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. That was the Reaſon, ſaid
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38018:69"/>
               <hi>Altophel,</hi> (who yet was troubled for the loſs of his Gold) that they overcame me, and ſo weak a Digeſtion as I have, ought to receive but little at a time. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, ſaid the ſecond Perſon, comes out of the Country, where a Speculative VVit is the only Allurement of Youth, whilſt it is common there; that in their Companies they toyl more at their <hi>Jeſts</hi> and <hi>Clinches,</hi> than we do in our greateſt Debauchments. No, ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> I think my Friend is of a more Refin'd Converſation than to be delighted in ſuch Traſh, and he has brought with him a Judgment whoſe greateſt Error is its perverſneſs. I was always, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Altophel,</hi> willing to Learn any thing that might be for my Advantage, but there is ſo little of Moment in what I find here to know, that I cannot ſo far over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Coyneſs of my Intellect as to Oblige it to admire it: This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſaid one of the other, ought firſt to be throughly Inſtructed in our grand <hi>Theſis;</hi> which is this, That Pleaſure is he only buſineſs of Life, ſince if he admits that, he will approve of all things that are Aids to our Diverſion; we have laid this Principle ſo low, that Juſtice and Fitneſs, ſame and Scandal, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38018:69"/>and Honour, are <hi>Chymaeraes</hi> that only hover beyond it, and are wholly unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to it. <hi>Altophel,</hi> ſaid <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> you are now in the Company of very admirable Perſons, and therefore, I hope, you will diligently apply your ſelf to their Inſtructions. I believe (ſaid the Squire) all things that you can ſay to their Advantage; and I have nothing to accuſe but my own Unhappineſs, that I am not worthy of the knowledge of thoſe excellent Endowments which theſe Gentlemen are ſo well furniſhed withal. There is ſo much flattery ſaid one of them in this Diſcourſe, that I wiſh it at an end, and I will contrive it by leading you the way out; with which they all went to the Play, of which one of thoſe Gentlemen was the Author; all along he opened the Excellencies of it to <hi>Altophel</hi> who ſat next him, and on the Bench behind them ſat a Company of Gentlemen, that Damn'd at the ſame rate which he Elogized. That Diſcord made up a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Harmony of Town Impertinence, for as the <hi>Poet</hi> on the one hand praiſed Extravagantly; ſo the <hi>Criticks</hi> on the other, Damn'd as unreaſonably. The Play was good, but the Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made it ſo Luſcious, and the Reproach
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38018:70"/>ſo Sowre, that it could not poſſibly go down with <hi>Altophel,</hi> he could not but think within himſelf that he ſhould at that Rate never be able to Learn any thing, whilſt it had ſo many Praiſes and Curſes hung about it; when all was done, the <hi>Poet</hi> told <hi>Altophel,</hi> that he might ſee with what Diſcouragements, and with how many Diſadvantages men VVrote in this Age; and that if he had a mind to write a <hi>Play,</hi> he would find enough to diſſwade him from that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, in the Adventure of that After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon. <hi>Altophel,</hi> to return the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, told him that he could never have the heart to aſpire to ſo great an Undertaking; but he ſhould never have the leſs Eſteem for an excellent Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe of the Ingratitude it meets with in the world. VVere not our Kindneſs for the Ungrateful world ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, replied the <hi>Poet,</hi> we ſhould never trouble our ſelves with doing any thing for ſo Capricious an Age; but the Comfort is, that we ever keep the good Opinion of the Ladies, what ever we Looſe from the Men. They, ſaid <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> never fall into Factions, and their Innocence and Sweetneſs makes them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38018:70"/>conſtant in what they eſteem for wit; and methinks it would be an Enterprize worthy of ſome great Sufficiency, to Damn the Cenſures of Men as Falſe and Erronious, whilſt all wit ſhould only ſeek the <hi>Patronage</hi> of the Ladies, and receive its ſame and Reputation from the gentle Plaudits of the Female hand. If we ſhould ſet them up alone, (replied the <hi>Poet</hi>) as the abſolute Judges of wit, ſo exceſſive a Power would cauſe in them the ſame Cruelty and Pride as is now found amongſt our ſelves, and to keep their Judgements in an equal Eſtimation, is the only way to receive from both Gentle, and Benigne Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; there is no Man that writes but ſtands in need of Pardon, and a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Cover his faults, which all Times allowed, till theſe have aſſumed a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Barbarouſneſs, in Stigmatizing the Blemiſhes of the beſt Wits, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever arranging them to their greater Perfections. It cannot but be expected (replied <hi>Altophel</hi>) but that the longer the World laſts the more it will abound with ill Nature, and there is no other Remedy can be found for ſo Unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Evil, but a happy and patient
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38018:71"/>neglect of it; as the <hi>Poet</hi> was a going to Reply, <hi>Rhoderick</hi> pulled him by the ſleeve, to turn him towards two Ladies, whom he found to be thoſe generous Perſons that had Supped with them the Night before. <hi>Altophed</hi> did the ſame, and at the ſight of him the Ladies broke into a Laughter, which put the Squire quite out of Countenance: I reſtored you your Breeches, Sir, ſaid one of them to him, I'le aſſure you I did not attempt to wear them, ſince I could not be ſatisfied that they would have helpt me to any amorous Thoughts, though (if I ſhould ſteal them again) perhaps I might not ſo eaſily defend my ſelf from that Curioſity, becauſe I may be of the Opinion that the Owner of them is ſometimes more extraordinary. <hi>Alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> knew not what reply to make to this free Diſcourſe; for he had too much Civility for a Tart, and too much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to make a wanton Repartee. <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> who knew him beſt, anſwered for him; and told the Lady, That his Friend ought to think himſelf happy that he had any ways Contributed to the Divertiſment of ſo fine a Lady, and he was (without doubt) deſirous of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:38018:71"/>thoſe glorious Occaſions of doing it this evening, which he had the laſt. With which words <hi>Rhoderick</hi> took her by the hand to lead her out, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers followed them.</p>
            <p>They went in the firſt place to walk in the Park, where all the Divertiſments of the place could not prevent the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieveous Lady, that had before been <hi>Altophels</hi> Tormentor, from making ſport with him again; ſhe had a great deal of Wit, and a Mind ſo exceſſively wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, that ſhe ſpake ſo many Smart and Arch things, as made the poor Squire Bluſh at a very extraordinary Rate; but thoſe were the moſt Gentle perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſhe intended that Night for <hi>Altophel;</hi> for after they had walked there ſome time, they went again into their Coaches, and were at laſt ſet down at the Houſe where one of thoſe Ladies lived; ſhe had reſolved to Treat the Company that Night, all the Servants being abſent but thoſe which were truſty to her Affairs; the great Schollar her Husband had reſolved to lie that Night at his Chamber, becauſe he was to riſe early the next morning upon a grand Trial, in which he was of Councel, he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38018:72"/>having this Occaſion, was ſo tender of his Wife, that he would not lie at Home becauſe ſhe ſhould not be diſturbed in her Repoſe, which was a very Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Reſolution; but Love which makes us Violate all Laws and Precepts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity and Gratitude; obliged the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Lady to make this ill uſe of her Husbands kindneſs, as firſt to bring ſuch lewd Company into the peaceful Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſo well diſpoſed a Gentleman, and then to Deſign it for the Theatre of very wicked Actions. They went im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to Supper, where they were very Merry, after that, they Danced and Played, and added a thouſand Frollicks to make their Extravagance compleat; and at laſt, after they had ſufficiently Tired and heated their Imaginations, they reſolved to Undreſs themſelves by conſent, and ſo to be ready for all other Extravagances they might think upon; the Ladies were the firſt Undreſſed, as having the greater Beauties to ſhew, and <hi>Rhoderick</hi> with his two Friends ſoon flung off their Clothes, that they might appear in ſo Graceful a faſhion, only the modeſt <hi>Altophel,</hi> like another <hi>Sir Nicholas Cully,</hi> was careful of every
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38018:72"/>Button, and of the tender Seams in his Coat, which one of the Ladies percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, very briskly came up to him, and told him ſhe would for once be his <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,</hi> which grand Honour the Squire could not in Civility decline: He was under her Hands when there was heard a great Knocking at the Gate, which was ſeconded by a more dreadful Noyſe at the Chamber-door, which cried <hi>my Maſter, my Maſter;</hi> this made a great Diſtraction in the Room, every one looked Amazed upon thoſe who ſtood next them, and they forgot to Glance wantonly upon thoſe Parts which they had ſhamefully expoſed, whilſt they haſtily took what Inſtructions they could get from each others affrighted Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but they had ſo little time for Conſultation, that they were forced to Execute the moſt Raſh and Unpreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated thoughts; the Lady of the Houſe flew quickly to her Smock, which ſhe did not light upon, but very careleſly took up <hi>Rhodericks</hi> Shirt inſtead of it, whilſt that Gallant <hi>Cavalier</hi> made his way through a Back door with a Laced Smock upon his Arm. <hi>Altophel</hi> fell to gathering up his ſcattered Clothes,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38018:73"/>and as he was ſtooping for his Stockings, one of the Ladies to get out of the Room fell upon him, and ſo they both lay ſtounded on the Floor; the reſt of the Company hid themſelves, ſome behind the Hangings, and others fled into Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, only <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> conſulting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly his own ſafety, flung himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Bed where the Lady of the Houſe uſed to lie, thither ſhe her ſelf came by another way, knowing it to be the beſt Retreat againſt a Capricious and Reproachful Husband. The good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman at laſt came up agaſhed with thoſe Apparitions he had met of a great Diſtraction, and the flying of Lights out of one Room into another. The Maid met him, and told him that her Miſtreſs was not Well, and that ſhe was in Bed; thither he went haſtily, and Condoled with her, in that Tragick manner, that <hi>Rhoderick</hi> broke out into a loud Laughter under the Bed; the good Gentleman being beſotted with his exceſſive Affection, thought his Wife had ſome ſtrange Fits of the Chollick, and therefore Ran haſtily from her to write for his Doctor. He went into the Dining-room where he found variety of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38018:73"/>Garments ſtrewed upon the Ground, which with a freſh amazement tore part of his miſerable Soul from the profound Grief that had ſeized it before; after he had wrote a few Lines for the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, he applied himſelf again to his Lady, for a Cure of thoſe Diſtractions he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had fallen into, but he did it in ſo Doleful a Tone, that <hi>Rhoderick</hi> again fell a Laughing, which he took for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of his Wives diſtemper, and ſo held his Tongue; but he was ſo uneaſie in himſelf, and his Wife (through the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement ſhe was in) returned his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes ſo ill-favour'dly, that he left the Bed and walked from one Room to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſtill as he came into a freſh Room he flung the Door to, which though it was an Action he did with no Premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but out of a ſecret Inſtinct of his Grief, that would hide him in his ill Humour from all the World, yet it had very pernicious Effects; for doing ſo in one Room, he ſtarted from behind the Door a Woman, who expoſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his ſight but an admirable ſhape and a fair Skin. This could not but augment his Diſtraction, ſince it was ſo difficult for him to Imagine of what ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38018:74"/>he ſhould define the delicate Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive, a Compoſition of the ſweeteſt Fleſh and Blood appeared to his ſight, but the diſorder of his Thoughts made him at firſt feign it to be an <hi>Eluſion,</hi> and a Shape aſſumed on purpoſe to heighten his Diſtractions; however he had the hardineſs to follow her, and ſhe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued her flight, and her ſhrieks till ſhe came into an Entry, where a Door and the darkneſs of the place made her think her ſelf ſomething ſecure; but the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer ſubmitting to an Impetuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, purſued her thither, and brought with him a Light great enough to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her true Proportion; the Lady had happened upon <hi>Altophels</hi> Retreat where he ſtood half Dead, and half Attired; the Lady clung to him, as cloſe as the amorous <hi>Ivy</hi> does to the Wall, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her Face in his boſome, ſhe indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ſet all her other perfections next the ſight of her Purſuer, well knowing it was only her Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Viſage that could betray a Perſon ſhe deſired to keep from his knowledge. <hi>Altophel</hi> perceiving the Light a coming, ſought a Protection from her he ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and ſhrinking his Head into her
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:38018:74"/>Boſome, he held her body as a Shield againſt all the blows he expected from a coming Adverſary. I can aſſure the Reader there was nothing amourous in theſe Embraces, which the extremity of fear had linked them in, nay, I mu t on the contrary confeſs, that <hi>Altophel</hi> behaved himſelf extreamly ill in this Action; for ſeeing the Danger of ſo fine a Lady, he ought to have ſtepped out, and to have offered himſelf againſt all that Inhumanity which came to Oppoſe her; but a great many ill Accidents had wholly diſpirited the Squire, and thoſe who are apt to reproach him for this Action, ought rather to deſire that they never happen into the like, leſt they ſhould come off with as ill a Grace. The Lawyer coming in, could not but be Scandalized at thoſe wanton Figures he beheld in the Entry, but he proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed farther, and endeavoured to pull them aſſunder, the Lady let go her hold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, and when ſhe was forced to do it ſhe clapped both her hands upon her face, and endeavoured to ruſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The Gentleman was ſo Nice that he would not catch her in his Arms to detain her, but let her go to be purſued
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:38018:75"/>by her own Shame and Fears. But he did not Treat the Squire ſo kindly, for he was reſolved to be perfectly Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in his Quality and Condition. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> at firſt very Maidenly put his Hand before his Face, but that would Protect him but a little while, and ſo he was at laſt forced to look as Big as he could upon his new Landlord; the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman having been more uſed to croſs-Queſtions than <hi>Altophel</hi> was to croſs-Purpoſes, ſoon Gravel'd the Squire, and got out of him the Knowledge of his Birth and Quality, but they ſtuck hard upon the Occaſion of his coming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Altophel</hi> ſaid at firſt, that he made Love to one of his Maids, but the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was ſo Impertinent, as to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her Name, which the Squire could by no means Diſcloſe. In ſhort, the Owner of the Houſe asked Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with ſo much Cunning, and <hi>Altophel</hi> replied in ſo much Confuſion, that he wrung the whole buſineſs from him, and there remained to him (as an Effect of his Ungentile curioſity) nothing but his own Shame and Reproaches. He Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Altophel</hi> at a very ſtrange Rate, and repeated all thoſe Advantages which
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:38018:75"/>the Law had given him over him, to which the Squire only replied (being now come ſomthing to himſelf) that if he would take the Advice of a Stranger, and one whom he believed to be an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, it was in ſhort this: That he would find his Reputation more advantagious to him, than his Revenge; and that the beſt Remedy againſt Diſaſters of that Nature, was Patience and a ſilent Quiet. But the Gentleman who had been uſed to make Chollerick and Keen replies, belaboured <hi>Altophel</hi> with an abundance of foul Language, to which he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſhort; That if he expected from him the Satisfaction of a Gentleman, he was ready to give it him, otherwiſe he muſt not take it ill if he forcibly made his way to his Clothers; and with that he took the Candle from the Lawyer, and went to make himſelf Ready. He knew that to call out, or to ſtop <hi>Altophel,</hi> would be but to have more Witneſſes of his ſhame, and he therefore careleſly ſet himſelf down in the dark, full of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction and Confuſion. The Squire haſtily put on his Clothes, and went out of the Houſe, without ſo much as asking for the reſt of the Company, or ſending
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:38018:76"/>them the Good-night. <hi>Altophel</hi> being the only Perſons, (whom the <hi>Writer</hi> is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to take care of) he might hope for an Excuſe, ſhould he leave the others to ſhift for themſelves; as for <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> he had a good Retreat, and might lie there ſecure till the Morning; and if the Maſter of the Houſe ſhould go to his Chamber, there is a much warmer and a much eaſier place at his Service, where he may if he pleaſe, Laugh louder at the fondneſs of an Indulgent Husband: The Lady who was naked had firſt thoſe Beauties to Protect her, which in any but Savage minds would rather procure her a Paſſion than Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Beſides, in ſome place of the Houſe are hid thoſe two Generous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers, that would with the hazzard of all things, bring her off with ſafety; and as for the Gentleman who had all the wrong, done him, I am ſenſible there are few Readers will be ſo much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for him, as to deſire he ſhould with any advantages come off from theſe Miſadventures, and after all this, there is pone but his Lady who requires our Aſſiſtance; but for that we may conſider that ſhe is left in a warm place, and a Gallant within her call: Moreover, ſhe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38018:76"/>hath uſed and ſtudied her Pleaſures too long, not to be furniſhed with the moſt Dexterous and beſt Excuſes for this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture; and ſhe is Beſides, a Lady of thoſe powerful Careſſes, which are ever Invincible arguments, againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of thoſe that are at any time out of Humour, or Capricious, and there is none who underſtand the admirable ſleights of ſuch Perſons, but can believe ſhe would ſcape the beſt of all, and that the moſt Officious Writer could not ſhew her ſo much aſſiſtance, as ſhe will receive from her own Arts. But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe things, of which I might frame a juſt Apologie for leaving them in this condition; yet I am willing to ſpare to my Reader, the trouble of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any thing in his own mind, which ſhould have been Dictated to him. The owner of the Houſe after ſome time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelf, and converted his other Diſtractions into Rage and Fury, which carried him with a great Noiſe about the Houſe; all ſhrunk at his approaches, though he would willingly have met with ſome Body on whom he might have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his fulneſs, either by Complaints or Railing, which when he could not
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:38018:77"/>find, he had recourſe to the Conſolation of an old <hi>Roman</hi> ſentence, crying out with <hi>Nero,</hi> at his Death, <hi>Ego nec Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, nec Inimicum habeo.</hi> The Naked Lady, who was within the ſound of that Diſtracted ſentences, was ſeized with a freſh trembling, fancying him to grow more Savage in his Latin, than he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Fury he expreſſed in his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tongue. Night and Fear ſtrangely aſſiſt our diſordered Fancies, to the fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of frightful Images, and this poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was ſo unkindly Treated by hers, that ſhe feared her late Purſuer would ſuddenly appear to her in a ſhape more Horrid and Monſtrous, than his own. How gladly would ſhe have welcomed to her Arms, any one that might have Reſcued her from theſe. Diſtractions, though they had brought with them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that Love which was due to her Beauty. It may be judged Inhumane to take any advantages on her preſent Diſorder, otherwiſe the Reader might make ſome Reflections for his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; for if ſuch an Encounter can raiſe up all theſe frightful Terrors in the Mind of a fair Lady, How much greater would be her Diſtractions, to ſee the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38018:77"/>black ſhapes of her Infamy and Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? and a wounded Vertue muſt to a noble mind, be a more dreadful ſight, than the ruines of a Repoſe or Fame? But ſince the Reader may not take it well to meet with this Digreſſion, we will only wiſh before we return to the relation, that the quiet of that amiable Sex may never be diſturbed, but on ſuch juſt Occaſions. The Lawyer went on complaining of his own and <hi>Neroes</hi> Misfortune, till he came at laſt into his Wives Chamber, and drawing near the Bed, he charged her with the ſame Mouthful of <hi>Latine,</hi> which a conſtant uſe had made her underſtand to have only the force of a Paper <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado.</hi> But <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> though he was a great Wit, yet being but a ſmall Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſt thought they had been going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome Conjuration, in which black Net he feared to be Caught at laſt, and therefore not to be taken Tardy, he reared up on the other ſide of the Bed; which the Lady (who had been more uſed to hear old Sentences than <hi>Rhoderick</hi>) not knowing the meaning of his appearance, entertained it with a great ſhriek, which together with the odd fight of that Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, obliged the Gentleman to fly back
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38018:78"/>in ſome diſorder, though ſuch as ought not wholy to debar him from the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes of making an honourable Retreat. For in ſuch caſes it is difficult to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine by what Rules of Honour the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhould be meaſured, for if he took the Cavalier for a <hi>Demon,</hi> as I never yet heard his Confeſſions in that particular, then his Flight was more Prudent than Inglorious, ſince we cannot but think that Beauty is at any time better Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to that Power, than an admirable Pleader; but if <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> we muſt ſtrain a little higher, to acquit him of the Reproaches that are due to an Ignoble fear, though it is known that ſuch Bullies are very Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to Men of his Intelligence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Collections. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> ſeeing his flight, and the Room void of an <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſt,</hi> took the advantage and Leaped o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Bed after him, making a ſtrange Noiſe to augment his fear; whilſt he was purſued he made a great Out-cry, all the Servants who knew the Buſineſs, went not to his Reſcue, but would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſuffered him to have been Torn in pieces, than to have acted againſt their Miſtreſs; ſuch a Treacherous and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38018:78"/>ingrateful Family, did this honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man feed with his Subſtance: But at laſt his Coachman (who was privy to none of theſe things) hearing the Out-cry of his Maſter, ran up ſtairs, where ſeeing him in a Scuffle with <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> he Reſcued him, and with his Whip ſoundly Laſht his Adverſary, who then was forced to turn Tail and Flie, whom he followed whilſt his Maſter lay half Dead on the floor. But <hi>Rhoderick</hi> being deſtitute of a Retreat, feeling the ſmart of the whip, and ſeeing but one to follow him (though naked and unarmed) yet turned agen and grew too hard for the Fellow, who then called out for his Maſter (as he had done before for him) who at laſt came to his aſſiſtance; with which new force <hi>Rhoderick</hi> was again overcome and ſoundly beaten by the Victors, which the other two Gentlemen hearing (though in a Naked condition yet) could not put up the Affront and Injury done to their Friend, but ruſhed out to his Reſcue, making a great Noiſe with the fall of thoſe things which had hid them; their appearance ſtruck a new fright in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe who were belabouring of <hi>Rhode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> and not knowing from whence
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:38018:79"/>they came, nor how many might follow them, they made their way haſtily out of the Room; as they were running, the Lady who was in the ſame Naked condition, thinking to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Diſorder which ſhe heard, ran juſt before them croſs an Entry, which affrighted them the more to ſee themſelves thus Invironed with naked Figures, they were a going to turn, but there they beheld the ſame ſhapes flying after them; the Lady took the ſame way they had deſigned, and ſo was purſued by the Owner of the Houſe and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, of whom <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and his friends were in Chaſe; they had all flung them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs down one pair of Stairs, when at the bottom appeared the faithful <hi>Jinny</hi> lighting up the Doctor (who was now come) to her Miſtreſſes Chamber, ſhe having a perfect knowledge of all things very prudently and kindly ſtepped out of the way to give them room in their flight; but the Phyſitian could by no means Imitate the Hardineſs and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of the <hi>Damoſel,</hi> but ſtanding ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and going at length to turn back, the nimble Lady flung her ſelf upon him, and flung him, down thoſe ſtairs, upon whoſe
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:38018:79"/>brink he was juſt Mounted; the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer and his Man were ſoon upon them, whilſt <hi>Rhoderick</hi> and his Friends made a halt at the top of the ſtairs, whom <hi>Jinny</hi> who beheld all theſe things very calmly, adviſed to take another way; but Honour was more powerful with them than the thoughts of their Safety, which Prompted them to work the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the Lady from that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhe was in, though in that affrighted Company there appeared no danger of her being Raviſhed; but Honour is Nice and Scrupulous, and ſo would not be ſatisfied but in their ſeeing the Lady out of Danger. They were plucking her from under them, when the Doctors man hearing the Out-cry of his Maſter, came in to his Reſcue, and having a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Link in his hand, he ſtruck at the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Bodies that ſtood before his Maſter, who not enduring the ſmart of fire were forced to run from it, after whom the others followed apace. No Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betwixt the moſt Gallant Perſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made Victory more Wavering and Irreſolute; for at one time ſhe pearcht upon the Lawyers ſleeve, and at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtood clapping her Wings upon the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38018:80"/>bald-pate of <hi>Rhoderik,</hi> but ſince the firſt was the Juſteſt ſide, whoſe Territories the others had Invaded, ſhe was at laſt beſt ſatisfied with Gracing him with her Favour, whoſe Enemies fled into a Chamber and there Locked the Door, reſolving to defend it to the laſt man, or otherwiſe to provide for their own Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Here the Beſiegers call'd a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, whether it were beſt to ſend for the Conſtable and his Troop, or to Invite the Beſieged to a Parley, which would be the moſt prudent way of Proceeding; And the Gentleman having ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the matter from <hi>Altophel,</hi> thought the firſt way would be but to put his Reputation into the hands of pitiful Fellows (which he might very well truſt with a Perſon of Worſhip, ſuch as his Doctor was) he therefore left the two Servants whilſt they went into another Room, and there after a Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Matter, they took that Councel which ſhewed them to be Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and good Natured Gentlemen; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they went to Viſit the Lady, for whom the Doctor was ſent for, who heard all the Noiſe, but knew the ſtorm would fall upon her ſelf, at laſt the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38018:80"/>felt her Pulſe, which quickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the diſorders of her Mind, he asked her ſome gentile Queſtions, and made her ſome Complements, telling her in the end, That at preſent he ſhould preſcribe her nothing, but according as ſhe reſted that night he might know what was neceſſary to be given her, and ſo he commended her to her Repoſe; but poor Lady! It was impoſſible for her to enjoy any of thoſe ſweet and balmy Slumbers, ſo many Diſtractions ſeizing at once on her Mind, as were able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the greateſt Inclinations to reſt; ſhe had paid ſo dear for the firſt Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Evening, by all the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs which ſucceeded them, that no one would have deſired to have took the Purchaſe from her: That Husband who loved her Infinitly, and whoſe exceſſive Affection had blinded him from a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row obſervance of her Actions, was now either diſobliged for ever, or elſe had that Jealouſie put into his Head, to which all her Life could be but one vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious Servitude, to which was added the loſs of that Reputation which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured her the Eſteem, and the Honour of her Friends. And it is certain, that
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38018:81"/>what ever Difficulties any may find in a ſtrict practice of Vertue, yet all who have not particular Obligations to their Infamy, will find a great many Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages and Pleaſures in an honeſt Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, of which this Lady found her ſelf deprived by the this unhappy Adventure; and ſhe hopes (for the <hi>Writer</hi> pretends to her Confidence) that all Perſons of her Sex and Conſideration, will by her Example be careful how they expoſe their moſt near Concernments for any of the unjuſt Delights of Love. But to return to the reſt of our Friends, thoſe who were ſhut up in the Room (for I muſt confeſs my holding Intelligence with both parties) conſulted amongſt themſelves, either to make a Salley at the Door, or out of the Window, though they were uncapable by reaſon of their naked condition to make a ſafe Retreat that way, they therefore reſolved to ruſh out at the Chamber-door, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Clothes, by which they might put themſelves into a condition for all Encounters; but the Lady who was ſhut up with them, by reaſon of her tenderneſs and her fears, enfeebled the Vigour of theſe Counſels; to her the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38018:81"/>ſucceſs appeared doubtful, but the blows certain from that Link whoſe ſmart ſhe had yet about her, which obliged them to fall to new Conſultations, which they had not ended before a welcome Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance was brought them, which they purchaſed without Blood-ſhed, and the peril of their Limbs; for the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having diſmiſſed the Doctor, he went to <hi>Jinny</hi> whom he knew to be the moſt in her Miſtreſſes favour, and what with Threats and his admirable Arts of Pumping, he drew out of her an account of all things, with the names of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and the diſtreſſed Lady; after which (full of Rage and Diſtraction) he went to his Chamber, and <hi>Jinny</hi> gave the ſign to the Beſieged to draw out, who made haſte to their Clothes, and having attired themſelves they all went to Condole with the poor Lady of the Houſe, who yet was uncapable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any Conſolation they could of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her, which with a few Complements that had alſo catch'd cold in the Naked condition of their Authors, they bid the Lady Good-njght, only ſhe prevailed with her Female Friend to be her Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow till the Morning, which ſhe was
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38018:82"/>very willing to do, becauſe ſhe was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the ſame Predicament with her ſelf, and ſo one Pillow might aid them in a mutual Counſel; they had both ſuch a ſhare in this Adventure, that what was good Advice for one, muſt needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come extreamly proper for the other, whilſt an inevitable Misfortune had at once two to deplore it. We will leave them to their Plots, not forgetting the great Sufficiency of the Female Wit in Contrivances of that Nature, though the Writer is too Impatient to attend the Succeſs of them, out of the real Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which he hath for any thing that is Diſhonourable in a Sex which he only eſteems for Vertue and juſt Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Of the Gentleman that went to his Chamber, we have no more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, but that he continued there in a great deal of Grief and Confuſion, not giving the next day that aſſiſtance in a Cauſe which he owed to a large Fee; though it is likely that was not the firſt Client he had ſo unkindly Treated. The Gentlemen who had run through all the Perils of that Night, arrived ſafe at <hi>Rhodericks</hi> Lodgings, where they all Refreſhed themſelves after their Toyls,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38018:82"/>being no whit Diſcouraged by thoſe Ill accidents, from Undertakings of the ſame Nature; only <hi>Altophel</hi> began now to be quite weary of that manner of Life, and the more he thought of it, the greater number of Inconveniencies came into his Memory to encreaſe his Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it; he was not ſure that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whoſe Houſe he was found, would not proceed in an Ungentile Manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, from which all his Courage and Generoſity could not bring him off wit h ſafety; but had his Fears of this been the ſlighteſt, yet he was too ſure of a very great Inconvenience, and that was the danger he was in of paying Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> he knew that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Friend of his took no care about ſuch things, but would very unkindly Expoſe him to thoſe Perils, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which muſt be a great Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his Parents, of whoſe Repoſe he was tender in all the Extravagancies he committed, for which he was much to be Commended; neither could the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirement of any thing he ſought to know, have Recompenced the Loſs of thoſe excellent Sentiments: He Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd up all the Ingenuity he had about
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:38018:83"/>him which earneſtly remonſtrated againſt every thing in which he miſpent his time and money; both which his Parents had committed to his own management and of which he could give but ill accounts. He had put <hi>Rhoderick</hi> in mind of what was coming on him; but he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to remove his fears by a thouſand proteſtations of that care with which he would protect him from all inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency in thoſe matters, but he knew that Money like Love often puts ſuch Perſons upon false Oathes who in all the refining of their Principles, conſtantly overlook that particular ſordidneſs: and therefore he thought it vain to confide in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes from <hi>Rhoderick</hi> which his opinion of honour did not oblige him to obſerve; and as for thoſe two opinions which young Gentlemen deſire to procure by the knowledge of ſuch things when they return home which are of Wit and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he was ſenſible that it could not be the collection of many things, but the judgement with which he expoſed them, that would procure him a juſt reputation of them, which the deſire of too many things rather ſpoyled by affectation than aided with a greater perfection; and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38018:83"/>therefore as long as he ſhould be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the lighter part of thoſe deſires, he reſolved to make as good an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as he could of his own judgment, though ſuch things like fading colours grow ſullyed with a little uſe, where they are not inlivened by the additions of a freſh paint, &amp; in theſe few ſpeculations he compriſed all his Town Adventures which could not but, appear leſs than the concernments of his Relation and affaires to which he now turned himſelf, with an ardent deſire of being governed by them, which he reſolved to do in the injoyment of his Friends and in the happy quiet of his Country.</p>
            <p>He communicated his Reſolution to <hi>Rhoderick,</hi> who parted from him with a great many Complements, and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his not ſhewing him more of the Town divertiſements, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed he would do if he might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon to make a longer ſtay in it; but thoſe conſiderations were not of ſuch power with <hi>Altophel,</hi> as to oblige him to alter his deſign of going home, he was ſenſible that he had committed too many extravagancies in the Town, to deſire any more ſhould be added to them;
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:38018:84"/>he found that he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had brought to that place too much youth, too much good nature, and too much mony, all which had betrayed him to very great inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies, ſince he had learned nothing there but what he might better have been without, and though the moſt Excellent and the beſt Endowments are there to be acquired, yet the Temptations to their Contraries being ſo numerous and ſo powerful, the odds are infinite of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing an ill, before a good Example. There is no admirable Quality, nothing that tends to the Gracefulneſs and the Embelliſhment of Youth, but is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently there expoſed both in an Illuſtrious Precept and a generous Example; but yet he that brings thither a Youth whoſe Paſſions are ſuperiour to its Judgement, will be firſt caught with thoſe infinite Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements that ſtand ready to Raviſh the Senſes, whilſt he takes no Impreſſions from the appearance of a plainer, though a richer Vertue. <hi>Rhoderick</hi> for his part could not but reproach the ſqeamiſh Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach of the Squire, which ſo ſoon Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeated thoſe things that he devoured with a perpetual Greedineſs; thoſe who always live amongſt ſuch Adventures,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38018:84"/>become by Cuſtome hardened to all the thoughts of a contrary Vertue, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quietly believe there is no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt good and Evil. To be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Pleaſed, and never to be out of Humour, is a Pleaſure they procure to themſelves by the moſt extravagant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but they purchaſe that Joy with too great a Treaſure, which is a <hi>Time</hi> that we can never enough value; we may eaſily believe that it is of that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable price, if we will pleaſe to conſider what great things we are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of doing with it, it is a light not ſet up for the World to Play and Revel by, not to Intoxicate our Souls with a Beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and a Hateful pleaſure, not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Murders upon Honour, nor Rapes on Innoconce; certainly, the World was leſs Deformed in it's firſt <hi>Chaos</hi> than with all thoſe horrid Shapes upon it: But time was given to the Earth for the affairs of Gratitude, and a publick Utility and Kindneſs; and particularly to Mankind, for the Management of an amiable Vertue, which is acquired by a thouſand Generous and Noble actions, and he that complys with none of thoſe Intereſts becomes more Ignoble than
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:38018:85"/>thoſe Beaſts he ought to Govern.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Altophel</hi> when he came Home, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Careſſes of his Friends whilſt the ſight of <hi>Aſtraea</hi> renewed in him the Vigour of his firſt Flame; that Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maid had, for the Love of <hi>Altophel,</hi> gone through the greateſt Difficulties that it was poſſible for a Perſon of ſo much tenderneſs to ſuffer; She with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Courtſhips of a Man that had purſued her with long and an unwearied Addreſs; She bore all the Diſpleaſures of her Parents, which ſhe Incurr'd by not Complying with their Will; and ſhe did all this for a man that Treated her neither with Civility, Juſtice, nor good Nature, but though ſhe found the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Ingratitude in <hi>Altophel,</hi> yet ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the ſatisfaction of her own mind a ſufficient Recompence for all ſhe did; he had left her in the moſt Unkind and Unhandſome manner that could be, he had never Writ to her all the time of their Separation; but againſt all theſe Diſcouragements ſhe believed that Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity was due to her own Reſolutions, which was not all a debt to <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tophel.</hi> But thoſe who admit into their Breaſts a real Kindneſs for any one, preſerve it there
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:38018:85"/>on the account of an agreeable inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and a juſt perſeverance; what ever faults <hi>Altophel</hi> committed were no Rule to her, when that youth came home, and had underſtood with how much real kindneſs <hi>Aſtrea</hi> had managed her ſelf, he admir'd her generoſity and Nobleneſs of mind, he confeſſed to himſelf, with a thouſand bluſhes, how barbarouſly he had wrong'd that amiable Virgin, and his ingratitude appeared the more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him, in thoſe diſſimulations and artifices he had met with in the Town, he readily confeſſed that the vertue and the kindnes of <hi>Aſtrea</hi> was worth all the world that a Love bound with ſuch happy liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is the greateſt treaſure upon Earth, and that the bounties of a vertuous mind can be never enough eſteemed, he addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf again to <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> and beg'd her to forget the Errors he had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to attribute them to the Vanity of his Youth, but it was too late for him to procure any thing from <hi>Aſtraea;</hi> ſhe wiſht him well, and ſhe was pleaſed to hear any thing of him that was to his advantage, and ſhe had rather ſee <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> happy than any Man in the world; but as for a Paſſion, which was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:38018:86"/>between thoſe that Commence a near Relation, ſhe found it not about her for that Youth; and ſhe would never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow her ſelf on a man whom ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſhe ſhould injure, in eſteeming him leſs than ſhe had done before; in ſhort, ſhe loved him too well to begin another Paſſion, on which ſhe was ſure ſhe could not look with ſo much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence as ſhe had done on the former; the firſt Deſigns of Love are ever the moſt perfect, ſince the ſecond attempt can never draw them with an equal Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Life: <hi>Aſtraea</hi> knew that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which had declined in her Soul, could never more reach that height it had firſt known; and to love <hi>Altophel</hi> leſs, would be a fault worthy of her own reproaches: Though ſhe had the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Kindneſs for him of all men Living, and that declined Eſteem was more than ſhe would ever have for any thing in all the World, yet ſhe judged it too little to be offered him: Love has but one way into our Souls, but Unkindneſs finds a Thouſand paſſages thither; and not only ſettles, but augments by thoſe ſecret ways that are unknown to our ſelves. <hi>Altophels</hi> Neglect and his great
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:38018:86"/>Injuſtice had blaſted the faireſt Bloſſoms of <hi>Aſtraeas</hi> Love, though ſhe had fed it with her Tears, and Cheriſh'd it with a careful remembrance; ſhe was ſenſibly afflicted to ſee it fade, whilſt ſhe found it impoſſible to recover it's former Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſhe arrived at laſt through ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accidents to a charming Stupidity of Mind, ſhe intended her own Honour and her own Decorum, and was Deaf to all conſiderations that ſuggeſted any thing to her contrary to that Deſign; ſhe reſolved to Live Unmarried, and though ſhe loved <hi>Altophel</hi> too well to have any man living beſides, yet ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that Kindneſs ſhe had for him, was not great enough to Oblige her to become his Wife. That Breaſt which is full of a true Glory, and a perfect Generoſity, is much harder to pleaſe in the Affection it has for another, than thoſe can be that would receive it with Tranſports from them; ſo great is the difference between a true Honour and an inglorious Diſſimulation; the firſt meets with the greateſt Difficulties in pleaſing it ſelf, whilſt to the other there remains no higher practices than the moſt plauſible Arts of Deceit; they
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:38018:87"/>who are aſſured that the Perſons whom they Love, are the poſſeſſors of a real Vertue, may reſt ſatisfied with all their Sentiments, ſince they will be as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to find out thoſe Errours in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as the moſt Capricious are ever ready to reproach them for. <hi>Altophel</hi> when he conſidered all theſe things in the Incomparable <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> and found her Reſolutions ſo ſettled as nothing could remove them, became ſo Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Generoſity of her Conduct, that he believed he owed her the proof of an equal greatneſs of Mind, in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving always Unmarried for her ſake. Theſe two may yet be ſaid to Love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, whilſt they eſteem each other above all the World, and wiſh the greateſt Happineſſes may be ſhared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, and yet they do all this with a Paſſion too cold to Unite in the Flames of <hi>Hymen. Altophel</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy to make thoſe Changes in a Heart which deſigned him ſo real a Kindneſs, but he was happy to make that Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which would always be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to a Noble mind, than all the Felicities of other Loves. So much more laſting are the Concernments of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:38018:87"/>our Vertue than thoſe of our frail Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites. No one was ever out Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour with thoſe good Qualities which they acquired by the moſt difficult deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of their leſs noble Inclinations, all the Hazzard is in declining at the firſt, an Enterprize which is ſo violently Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Paſſions, but when it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, there are too many Charms in the purſuit ever to admit a Repentance for the doing of it. No one will accuſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraea</hi> (for whom the Writer is paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Concern'd) for this manner of acting. <hi>Altophel</hi> did enough to abate the Vigour of her Love, and ſhe was Noble not to give at laſt any thing leſs-to <hi>Altophel,</hi> than ſhe had at firſt aſſured him: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we our ſelves, when we calmly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our own Breaſts, would be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to put thoſe we Love, to the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of dealing Forcibly with their own Inclinations. That Kindneſs which comes freely, and which is pleaſed with it's own Greatneſs, ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Tranſports; but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which is Conſtrained, and only Blowed to a Flame by violent Importunities, looſes the Pleaſures of it's Heat. If I have obtained a Candid Sentiment for <hi>Aſtraea,</hi>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:38018:88"/>and done any thing that may procure an Eſteem of her Character, I have reacht all the Pleaſure I Deſign'd in Writing the fore-going Pages. It is for that Generous Maid I am wholly Concerned, and if I have committed no Faults in the Draught of the Amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> I ſhall be leſs Diſturbed for all the other Errors of an Author.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38018:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
